<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true narrative and manifest set forth by Sir Robert Walsh knight and Batt. which he is ready all manner of ways to justify as relating unto Plots, designs, troubles and insurrections, which were intended to have been set a foot, towards the subversion of His Most Excellent Majesties laws and government, not by a private information, or other, but before any court of Justice, discipline ; either in the civil, common, or marshal law and to reply or disanul the printed paper, in part of Edmund Everard and Irish man, who was so long prisoner in the tower : and to make out why he was so detained, nothing relating to the plot but was for his intent to have poysoned the Duke of Monmouth as shall more amply be made out in this manifest.</title>
            <author>Walsh, Robert, Sir.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 118 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67448</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W644</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6905</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13506566</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13506566</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99819</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67448)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99819)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 480:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true narrative and manifest set forth by Sir Robert Walsh knight and Batt. which he is ready all manner of ways to justify as relating unto Plots, designs, troubles and insurrections, which were intended to have been set a foot, towards the subversion of His Most Excellent Majesties laws and government, not by a private information, or other, but before any court of Justice, discipline ; either in the civil, common, or marshal law and to reply or disanul the printed paper, in part of Edmund Everard and Irish man, who was so long prisoner in the tower : and to make out why he was so detained, nothing relating to the plot but was for his intent to have poysoned the Duke of Monmouth as shall more amply be made out in this manifest.</title>
                  <author>Walsh, Robert, Sir.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 3-35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to "The depositions and examinations ... concerning the  ... popish plot."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Everard, Edmund. --  Depositions and examinations ... concerning the horrid Popish Plot.</term>
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99819:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99819:1"/>
            <p>A TRUE NARRATIVE AND MANIFEST, <hi>Set</hi> forth by Sir Robert Walſh KNIGHT and Ba<hi rend="sup">TT.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which he is ready all manner of ways to juſtify, as relating unto Plots, Deſigns, Troubles and Inſurrections, which were intended to have been ſet a Foot, towards the Subverſion of His Moſt Excellent Majeſties Laws and Government, not by a private Information, or other, but before any Court of Juſtice, Diſcipline; Either in the Civil, Common, or Marſhal Law, and to reply, or diſanul the Printed Paper, in part of <hi>Edmund Everard</hi> an <hi>Iriſh</hi> man, who was ſo long Priſoner in the Tower.</p>
            <p>AND To make out why he was ſo detained, nothing relating to the Plot, but was for his intent, to have Poyſoned the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> as ſhall more Amply be made out in this Manifeſt.</p>
            <p>Printed for the Author, 1679.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:99819:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99819:2"/>
            <p>AS truth is truth, thoſe who perſiſt therein are the Sons of God, and ſuch as to the contrary go, doubtleſly time will show the effects, what is due to God, let us pay, and in what is our Anointed Kings, let us obey. I am his Subject and renounce his Grace, if diſloyalty can be laid to my face; Religion leads me unto this tenent, ſo should it Man-kind, the great Turk hath his Law, to keep his Subjects in due awe. Give <hi>Caeſar</hi> his due that is the thing, from which Loyalty doth ſpring; our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred King is juſt, and above all, may give the Law to riſe or fall, in the protection of his true Subjects, a true Proteſtant he is out of all doubt, any thinks other is but a Lout. Her Gracious good Majeſty is our Queen, our duty to her should be ſeen, and own'd ſo as no malignant tongue, may not lead us along, but into what is juſt, in Religions many opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions there be, His Majeſty ſtrives to let us ſee, that the Proteſtant Religion he will uphold, if we in duty do not grow cold, weowing Allegiance un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our King, ſo let us pay him and his, as in true Religion we are bound unto, let criminals their fate endure, and Innocents receive their cure. As ſo what is it we Subjects can groan under, let us but conſider and look of our Neighboring Subjects, their Poverty Slavery and Miſery, then look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the now Subjects of His Sacred Majeſties, King <hi>Charles</hi> the ſecond, and upon the happineſs of his Reign, have we wanted either in trade or ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did ſubſiſtance, when moſt of the world, have been in war and full of miſery, and our Alarums in breading confuſions. O the diſatisfaction of man
<pb facs="tcp:99819:3"/> when not contented, never compriſing when he is well, this I intend not to prevent or avoid pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cautions; our Sacred King is moſt certainly our Head, and where can lodge his intereſt, ſurety or ſafety, but in the uphold protection and preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Loyal and good ſubjects, for as he is the Head, the Body cannot ſubſiſt but in him, and by him, would not the ſon and true heir of a Subject, think it a hard uſage and dealing, that he ſhould laſt the effects of a crime, and hazard a conviction therein, ere he where ſummond to appear or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, if this may be allowed, how much more doth it regard the true intereſt of a Prince, (is unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niable) why did <hi>Pilate</hi> condemn <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but becauſe he ſtayed not to hear the truth, O what can be ſaid of the times, but ſtrange his Royal Highneſs being brought on the Stage, whoſe Name, Fame, Glory, Vallor, and Gallantry, hath eſclatted through <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope.</hi> He from his Minority did never refrain from the hazard of his moſt Royal Perſon fairly to win all applauſe, nay his ſubſiſtance in Foreign Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, what hath not he done, for the ſafety, honor and Glorious preſervation both by Sea and Land, of his Nation and His Sacred Majeſties good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. If there be any who knoweth not this, ſure he is a ſleep, (but they are not,) who are Villains, and Impudent Raſcals, that moſt libellouſly ſet forth in Pamphlets, to ecclipſe his due and rights, ſuch who take that liberty what would they not be at, to emote troubles and diſturbances in His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Kingdoms and Dominions. Were I ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond to appear before the face of Juſtice, or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb facs="tcp:99819:3"/> in Power, I could atteſt &amp; prove, that in the year 72. and 73. how ſome of His Moſt Excellent Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Subjects, have been trampling, indeavoring and abetting, to raiſe inſurrections, tumults and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbances, in His Moſt Excellent Majeſties King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and Dominions, to the intent of ſubverting His Majeſties Fundamental Laws and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and I am ready to prove that his Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, was ſo much a ſtranger and unknowing in the ſaid intermedlings, as nothing could be more, ſome malignant ſpirits, will ſenſure what I hear ſay to be a Paradox, to the contrary I am ready to make ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, nay more, that if the ſaid inſurrections had proceeded or gone on, I will make out or forſe it my head, If that his Royal Highneſs would not be the firſt, that would hazard his Life and perſon to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and ſuppreſs the ſaid intendments, had I been interrogated when I was in the Moneth of <hi>May</hi> laſt 79. ſummond to appear, as I have at the Bar of the Honorable Houſe of Commons, as I was before ſummond, nay carried Priſoner to the Black Rod, and appeared before their Moſt Honorable Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of the Houſe of Lords, I would not have ſtuck to have made mention, of what came within my knowledge, as I am ready to do, and maintain what is here adjoyning ſet forth in my manifeſt, may <hi>I</hi> but be allowed the true liberty of a Subject, I come not in as an Informer but to pay my Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, without pretence of Benefice or Promotion, Honor enough I have, the mark of which I carry at my Breaſt for which I have His Majeſties of Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Memory's Commiſſion to carry, &amp; wear in any
<pb facs="tcp:99819:4"/> colour Blue, Green or Black, in the later <hi>I</hi> do not, having never been guilty of any action of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, for the ſins of my Youth <hi>I</hi> have, for which <hi>I</hi> ask God only pardon. As unto the honor of my Knight-hood, ſome when they want diſcourſe and to derogate from me, vvill ſay that it vvas Sir <hi>John Smith</hi> vvho vvas Knighted the day of Battle at <hi>Edge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill,</hi> and ſo he was, vvho vvell deſerved it; that Royal Prince of the Blood, his Highneſs Prince <hi>Rupert, I</hi> am confident vvill pleaſe to remember, as unto this vvhat <hi>I</hi> ſay in my manifeſt, his Highneſs being the Perſon, that introduced me unto his Majeſty up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the top of <hi>Edge-hill,</hi> vvhere his Majeſty did then honor me vvith the title of Knight-hood.</p>
            <p>Thouſands of Prints are cryed up and down, but they will n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t as I do ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe their names to their Prints, to juſtifie in Juſtification of their malignity, as I do of my Loyalty.</p>
            <p>In this my Manifeſt may be read, part of Sir <hi>Robert Walſh</hi> his life, carriage, actions and ſufferances. Enemies enviouſly and ungroundedly he hath had, who now are disbanded into the other world, yet if any particular man carry any animoſities againſt him, he knowing not of any ground or Subject he hath given, he is ready to ſatisfie any that may pretend to the contrary, leaving thoſe who read this, to judge the hardneſs of the meaſure he hath met with, wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he may be the ſole, or only in this Age, who may find the Effects of the like Injuſtice as he hath.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:99819:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THis manifeſt of Sir</hi> Robert Walſh, <hi>doth declare that he cant out of</hi> France <hi>into</hi> England <hi>in the Year 1675. not without order; as he can make it appear (where his Loyalty and Duty did ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liege him) and alſo to declare, what malignant deſignes and inſurrections, were Ingendring in</hi> France, <hi>where he lived moſt of his time theſe Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and odd years, towards the ſubverſion of His Moſt Excellent Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Government, and Fundamental Laws, and he hath here continued theſe Four Years and above, to make out what his manifeſt doth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto relating, ſet forth; Remonſtrating nothing but what came within his knowledge, and what he is ready to juſtifie, not only by Oath, but by the Laws of any Courts of Juſtice, as either in the Civil, Common or Marſhal Law, to the face of any Subject, any</hi> French, Dutch, <hi>or Forreigner. And is ready to declare if ſummond thereunto; how that in 72. 73. and 74, ſome of his Majeſties Subjects have been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termedling therein, preſuming that they may be countenanced and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held, by a greater perſon then yet hath been quoted, or named, to have fomented in the ſaid Troubles. Sir</hi> Robert Walſh <hi>having taken his diſmiſs and paſs from the</hi> French <hi>Kings ſervice, being in no truſt of his, Sir</hi> Robert <hi>by His Moſt Excellent Majeſties permiſſion, and orders of ſome of his chief Miniſters of State, did keep Intelligence out of</hi> France, <hi>with Mr.</hi> Edward Progers <hi>one of his Majeſties grooms of the Bed-chamber; as ſhall be made amply out, in this manifeſt. As alſo how this</hi> Everard <hi>and for what he was made Priſoner in the Tower, which he chargeth the Lady</hi> Anne Gordon, <hi>Collonel</hi> Richard Talbot, <hi>and his Brother, to have been the Contrivers of his Impriſonment, ſome particulars in his depoſitions ſhall be proved moſt falſe, and he hath no way to Juſtifie himſelf. Unleſs, that as he doth profeſs himſelf to be very dextrous in his weapon; that by that he may ſecond his Oath. In all Kingdoms, ſome Subjects are good, and ſome not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>What Subject in this Age, hath proved more true, then the Duke of</hi> Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond, <hi>give him his due: ſome are bad, and yet I hope there may be made a true difference, in ſome particulars it may be demonſtrated, the marks of their Loyalty conferred upon ſome Iriſh, as thus. There is the Lord</hi> Coorſy, <hi>who by His Majeſties Authority, is ordered and permitted, to wear his Hat in His Majeſties Preſence; certainly it was for his Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, that that honor was conferred on him, of which this day the young Lord</hi> Coorſy <hi>may be covered before His Majeſty, which is for the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable ſervice he hath rendred the King and Crown. Nor hath Sir</hi> Robert Walſh <hi>the priviledge of wearing His Majeſties of Bleſſed Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory His Effigies, and that of his deareſt Son Prince</hi> Charles, <hi>of the</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:99819:5"/> 
               <hi>one ſide of his Golden Medal; and the form of His Majesties Royal Bannor of the Reverſe, but for the Acceptable Service he hath rendered at the Battle of</hi> Edge-Hill, <hi>in the year 43. as his Commiſſion for wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame from His Majeſty of Bleſſed Memory now Exſtant, can wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, he having received the Dignity and Honor of Knight-hood, upon the Top of</hi> Edge-Hill. <hi>Sir</hi> Robert <hi>being Born in</hi> Ireland, <hi>I hope may not paſs for a Crime, though ſome of the Follies of his Youth may be thrown in his Diſh, as the ſin of the Fleſh, and Gaming, yet never was any crime of Dis-Loyalty. The firſt of his Name that went from</hi> England <hi>into</hi> Ireland, <hi>for His Majeſties Service in King</hi> Edwards <hi>Time, was Sir</hi> Patrick Walſh, <hi>who to Attack the City of</hi> Lymberick, <hi>cauſed a Hundred Horſe and Men, to ſwim over the River of</hi> Shannon, <hi>and ſo Surprized and Took</hi> Limberick; <hi>as the Chronicle of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Ireland <hi>more largely Expatiates upon. But Sir</hi> Patrick <hi>a Horſe-Back, ſwimming over the River, Bows and Arrows then being in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe, he ſhot a Swan Flying, through the Breaſt, ſo as ever ſince the flying Swan hath been his Creſt, with the Arrow through the Swans Creſt, and his Armes three Arrows Heads; which hath ſo continued to his line and Name; as now they do in me; which I give with an addition of the</hi> flowers De-luce, <hi>which I give by the right of having Married an Heireſs, and I being in</hi> France <hi>then in command, having a Regiment in His Chriſtian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Service, and His Moſt Excellent Majeſty then being in</hi> Paris <hi>and in the</hi> Louure; <hi>ſome</hi> Theſes <hi>being dedicated at the Colledge of</hi> Cerbone, <hi>unto the Nobleſt and beſt of His Moſt Excellent Majeſties Subjects. There was one Dedicated to me, by one of the Doctors in Theology of the ſaid Colledge, and my Arms being ſet forth and diſplay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, carrying the</hi> Flowers De-luce, <hi>and my name being</hi> Valois, <hi>and ſo was when in the Conqueſt the name came out of</hi> France <hi>into</hi> England, <hi>which here is turned to</hi> Walſh; <hi>by time, the Duke</hi> De Anguleme <hi>being</hi> De Valois, <hi>which name have been Kings of</hi> France, <hi>ſome being curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſent to the</hi> Louure, <hi>to know, if I was not</hi> de La Maiſon de Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lois, <hi>as ſome Noble-men now here may pleaſe to remember, then heard the queſtion propounded, ſo as ſome who grumbled that I ſhould be named</hi> Valois, <hi>may here be ſatisfied upon what ground I went by the ſaid name, and not as</hi> un nom de guere, <hi>ſome who may read this, will underſtand why I thus Expatiate. Another thing Summons me to this Manifeſt, ſome whom I cannot call better than Lyars, Cowards, and Villains, who if any of them be living and read this, they will ſwallow my Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Thoſe I mean, who have villainouſly, and moſt falſly invented, that I was hired by</hi> Cromwel, <hi>and the Lord of</hi> Brohill, <hi>now Earl of</hi> Orery, <hi>to Kill my Sacred and Anointed King, as I at large ſet out in my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt. I having been Murderouſly detained Priſoner in</hi> Bruxels <hi>Thirty Three Months upon that falſe pretention, I renouncing the leaſt Grace or Fav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r from His Sacred Majeſty, then as now I do, if any Dis-Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty could or can be laid to my Charge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>If I herein be prolix, pray Noble Reader pardon it, and conſider, if that my unjuſt and non-parell ſufferances in thoſe days, may not plead</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:99819:5"/> 
               <hi>my excuſe, and withal that in this my following Manifeſt, or Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance, doth not carry in it a word of untruth, nor other then what I am ready to juſtifie with my life and fortune. unto my new, or late repreſentments, I may add ſome old, which may not be unremarkable, as one at the Battle of Edge-Hill, in the Year 43. It lay fully in my power to have ended then that unhappy war of</hi> England, <hi>and for the ſupream advantage of my King; you will ſay why I did not do it, and I ſay when you read what followeth, you will own me not condemnable. As thus, at the ſaid Battle, as thoſe who were there do know, as the moſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Valiant Lord</hi> Gerart, <hi>Edward Earl of</hi> Barkſhier, <hi>and Collonel Edward</hi> Villers, <hi>Sir</hi> Edward Brett, <hi>Sir</hi> Thomas Daniel, <hi>and others, and the Lord</hi> Warton <hi>can alſo witneſs, that our left wing of Horſe then Commanded, by the moſt Loyal and Royal Earl of</hi> Brandford, Henry <hi>the Lord Wilmot, and Commiſſary General of the Horſe, did clearly beat, and put to flight the right wing of the Enemies, purſuing them through the Village of</hi> Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, <hi>which lay in the rear of the Enemies Army, being a long Village conſiſting of thatched Houſes; between which, then lay the Enemies Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition, ſome Cannon, and their Waggons; we purſuing the Enemy fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our foot in body, and the Enemies then hotly ingaged, order came to our Horſe, not to purſue the Enemy further, but to return to our Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. Our reſerve of Horſe unpremeditatedly coming with us in the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit: In our return through</hi> Kington <hi>Village, it came into my head, that the burning of that Village and their Ammunition, would have rendered us that days victory: Whereupon I ordered my Horſe men a foot, and to fire the Village and their Ammunition, and juſt as they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to ſet fire, the Honorable and Worthy Brave Lord Carnarvan, and that Worthy Commander Sir</hi> Charles Lucas, <hi>being my Superior Officers, commanded me from putting my reſolution in Execution, Saying, that the day was ours, as alſo that Ammunition and Village. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto which I made anſwer, that the Armies being then in fight,</hi> fortuna de la guere <hi>may be Subject to change the face and State of Affairs, and that the Burning of their Ammunition, could not but aſſuredly render his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty Supream Victory; yet notwithſtanding I was forced to give obedience, ſo as by the ſaid Ammunition, and Cannon, we were forced to retreat and quit the Field. However I then brought from</hi> Kington <hi>Two Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of their Cannon into the Kings Army; and the Waggon of my Lord of</hi> Eſſex, <hi>which was ſo compleat and made Coffin way; that in our next two days march, our Army called it</hi> Eſſex <hi>his Coffin, but I would it had been the next Waggon which was to it, covered with Spits and Frying<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pans, for there lay all the Armies money and pay; as one</hi> Pudcy <hi>who was Chamber-man unto</hi> Eſſex, <hi>who writ to me for his Lords neceſſaries, ſome days after did aſſure me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Though many more deſervedly then I, might in the day of Battle have attained to the Dignity of the Mark of Honor, I carry at my Breaſt; I am confident that there is not many, who can ſhow as ample a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of his Majeſties of Bleſſed Memory for the like, as I have now Extant; which in this particular it hath profited me in: Where all No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemen
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99819:6"/> and Knights are liable to pay pole mony, I having ſent my badge, Title, and Commiſſion unto thoſe worthy Commiſſioners, who were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted in the aſſeſſment of the Pole-money; they then ſitting at</hi> Hicks'<hi>s</hi> Hall <hi>in</hi> May 1678. <hi>They were civily pleaſed to diſcharge me from the payment for my Dignity; and that I ſhould pay only a Shilling for my Pole, ſigned by two of the Commiſſioners, and ſealed, whom I yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to my knowledge did ſee.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Sir <hi>Ed. Abney,</hi> and <hi>William Beverſham,</hi> Commiſſioners the 29. <hi>May 1678.</hi> So in paying a Shilling I was quit.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:99819:6"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>EADER, pray be ſo juſtly favorable, I being forced in Honor and Loyalty to make this pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication, who am no Orator to judge, but with an indifferent eye, according to the proofs I of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, which I will maintain, ſtand unto, and will juſtifie, by Common, Civil, or Marſhal Law; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all Perſons and in all reſpects, and in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar againſt this <hi>Everard;</hi> as in any thing, wherein he doth bring in my name, he is a perſon that I have known of a long time; as alſo his condition, not by the qualification he aſſumes to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the title Eſquire; in his prints, as ſo he hath ſubſcribed his name, which I cannot imagine on what account; and I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that he hath as much right ſo to name himſelf, as unto the contrary he hath to have brought my name in queſtion, as to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the diſcovery of the Plots, in ſuch as he hath mentioned me in. If he will but take example in following my Rule, as now I find it not unneceſſary to explain my quality, and Title; and that he may truly ſo demonſtrate his, whereby the world may cenſure, or give applauſe, which as unto their judgments may ſeem fit. This <hi>Everard</hi> doth ſet forth in his ſaid depoſitions, that in the Year 1673. being in <hi>Paris,</hi> that he did diſcover unto me ſome deſigns, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbances, which were intended towards the prejudice of his Moſt Excellent Majeſtie's Kingdom, which as he ſaith, he came to the knowledge of from the Lady <hi>Anne Gourdon;</hi> a Lady that to my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance I never ſpoke unto, but heard of her as of a Lady of great Judgment, Birth, and quality; whoſe Family hath always been adorned with the endowments and Characters of Loyalty, of which ſome of late have given dmonſtration and Teſtimony of, as that Noble Perſon my Lord <hi>Donbarton</hi> and his Brother; ſo as if this Lady ſhould ſo fall off, as to intermeddle in the like unſeemly inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medlings; certainly ſhe hath degenerated and rendered her ſelf to be much ſenſurable, and to have done it unto ſuch a Perſon as this <hi>Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard;</hi> it could render her no leſs than ridiculous. But malice and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention hath ſo powerful an influence in this Age. <hi>Quod nihil plus.</hi> I ſpeak not as to take this Ladies part, nor to excuſe her weakneſs as I believe not, ſhould ſhe be guilty. But when I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that man reduced to poverty, Extremity, want, and miſery, as ſometimes this <hi>Everard,</hi> ſubject to ſearch after all manner of reſorſe for his relief, I will not take on me to Judge of the ſequel. Now as unto what he hints, as having in the Year 1673. diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto one Sir <hi>Robert Walſh,</hi> I knowing no other, may preſume he darts at me. Though he mentions not my ſtile or quality; pardon Noble Reader, If for reaſons I think it not incongruous; but rather inducing to conſequence, that it might be allowed, my precations grounded upon Honor, may not be involved in other then in duty, and Loyalty, unto my Anointed King; in whoſe ſervice, I have had the Honor to have born very conſiderable charges, and imployments,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99819:7"/> ſince the Year 1639. in the firſt Northern ſervice, under the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the now Lord <hi>Stafford,</hi> having ever ſince ſerved my Kings Honorably, and Faithfully (which no body can deny) and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly in the Battle of Edge-Hill, in the Year 1643. Where fate was no leſs favorable unto me, then fortunate in inabling me to render my King acceptable ſervice; ſo as that he was then graciouſly pleaſed in the Field, to honor me with the dignity of Knight-hood; then giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Royal Commands, that when he ſhould arrive in <hi>Oxford,</hi> that a Medal of Gold ſhould be made for me, with his own Effigies, and that of His Deareſt Son Prince <hi>Charles</hi> of the one ſide: and to inſcribe thereon, <hi>Carolus Rex, Magnae Britanniae, &amp; Carolus Princeps,</hi> And of the other ſide to inſculp the form of his Royal Bannor, uſed at the ſaid Battle, and to inſcribe about it, <hi>par regale mandatum Careli Regis hoc aſſignatur</hi> Roberto Walſh; which his Royal Majeſtie of Bleſſed Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory gave me accordingly, out of his own hand, and his Royal Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion for me to wear the ſame, expreſſing in it, that it was for the moſt acceptable ſervice that I rendred at the Battle of Edge Hill, which accordingly I have ever ſince worn; this was not gain'd by love or favor, <hi>ſedex officio gladii,</hi> which no Herald can deny, but may carry the title of right Honor, and now to be upbraided by <hi>Everard</hi> or any ſuch, Noble Reader, do but Judge, if it may well by me, be dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, were I guilty of the leaſt diſloyalty, I would condemn my ſelf, more then any accuſer could make me.</p>
            <p>Now as to this <hi>Everard,</hi> he did about the Year 1673. in <hi>Paris,</hi> come often my lodging, I then uſually making uſe of him, to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate for me <hi>Engliſh</hi> into <hi>French,</hi> as I have divers of his tranſlations in writing now by me, and extant, and then ſometimes gave him half a Crown; he coming from one end of <hi>Paris,</hi> the <hi>Reu de</hi> St. <hi>Antoine</hi> to the <hi>Saubourge</hi> of St. <hi>Jermins</hi> often unto me, the Half-Crown did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite him, not as it ſeem'd his love to me; and one night he did ſay, and at random, that great deſigns were intended to breed great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbances, in His Moſt Excellent Majeſties Kingdoms, without ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying upon what particular grounds, or making mention in the leaſt degree that he had any intention to diſcover them, but much to the contrary, vowing that he was reſolved to live and die, as he ever was bred in the Roman Religion; I then did repreſent unto him, that as he was a Subject of His Moſt Excellent Majeſties, and a Vaſſal born in the Country <hi>Palatine</hi> of <hi>Tipperary,</hi> under his Grace the Duke of <hi>Ormond,</hi> that he would do but his duty, if he knew any ſuch immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious intended, to give me notice whereby to advertiſe his Grace; which he then promiſed he would, but never after did he ever come at me or near me. Some time before, I had from a very conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hand, that there were then ingendring in <hi>Paris,</hi> to breed diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances in his Majeſties Kingdoms, towards the ſubverſion of His Moſt Excellent <hi>Majeſties</hi> Laws and Government, in which ſome of his Subjects were very officiouſly intermedling. I then did immediately addreſs my ſelf unto the <hi>marquis de Molac,</hi> who was my friend, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99819:7"/> one of his Royal Highneſs the Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> his Chief Gentleman, who did introduce me unto his Royal Highneſs, unto whom I did then repreſent that ſome Ingins were ſet a foot, to beget Tumults and Diſturbances in His Mageſties of great Britain his Kingdoms 1672. and that I did hope his Royal Highneſs, would ſpeak unto his Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Majeſty not to give ear, or countenance unto ſuch His Majeſties Subjects, as may therein be made abettors, or incendiaries: Though I was perſwaded, that they were therein countenanced, as I could make Oath, his Royal Highneſs did promiſe me, he would ſpeak unto his Brother, and that he would cary a diligent and careful eye thereunto, which with Juſtice I may ſay, that his Royal Highneſs would not this day diſown. Now in as much as that this <hi>Everard</hi> doth ſet forth in his depoſitions, that I moſt unfaithfully did betray him unto the Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bots, a thing I had no ground for, he not communicating unto me, that he had any ſuch intention, but much to the contrary, he and, they being much together, and upon the word of a man of Honor and the Faith of a Chriſtian I never did, nor was I but once all the time the Talbots were in <hi>Paris</hi> converſant with them, nor have I had any intimacy with Collonel <hi>Talbot</hi> or his Brother, but rather to the contrary, as ſome of my Kings beſt Subjects, I preſume may confirm. Now in as much as that <hi>Everard</hi> in his depoſitions maketh Oath, that he was made Priſoner in the Tower by the means of the Talbots, and the Lady <hi>Anne-Gordon.</hi> In that Alegation he contradicts himſelf, for after his enlargement from the Tower, he meets me in St. <hi>James</hi>'s Park; comes to me and cries, Sir <hi>Robert Walſh</hi> you are the man who put me into the Tower, and that made me a great ſufferer there, I then told him I was, and were it to do again I would; and that I did wonder how ſuch a Villain, that had ſo malignant intentions towards the Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi> could obtain his liberty; I did not then know that he had charged the Lady <hi>Anne,</hi> or the Talbots to have been the cauſers of his Impriſonment, and ſo we parted. Now to come to the true grounds of his being made Priſoner in the Tower, which ſhall be juſtified and made out: There was in the Year 1673. a Gentleman in <hi>Paris</hi> one Mr. <hi>Dalonſon,</hi> a perſon born unto a good eſtate, and now in the poſſeſſion of it, he being in <hi>Paris,</hi> very much reduced unto ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, he came to me declaring who he was, naming ſome friends of his that I well knew, and for whom I had eſteem, he demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſad condition he was in, I did take him to an Ordinary or eating-houſe, where I had credit a <hi>La ren de Colombie,</hi> and did give him credit for his Diet, and lodging in the ſaid oberge, where he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted two or three Months, and truly I did diſcharge him, as I am ſure he will own.</p>
            <p n="3">III. About the ſame time, <hi>Everard</hi> and this <hi>Dalonſon,</hi> coming both at a time to my lodging, they became acquainted, and ſo great an inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy in a little time they grew into, as that they joyned to lodge in a houſe, and in one Bed; and they two became as hand and glove. Some time before this <hi>Everard</hi> having the <hi>French</hi> Tongue, was intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99819:8"/> to his Grace the Duke of <hi>Monmouth;</hi> and in a little time, his Grace took him into his Service, to be his Sollicitor or under Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary; he having before been an under Clark to the Lievtenant <hi>Crime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel,</hi> or Lievtenant <hi>Civel</hi> of <hi>Paris</hi> I well know not which, how he did demean or miſdemean himſelf under his Grace, I know not, but caſt or caſhiered from the Dukes Service he was, and Mr. <hi>Sarchevel</hi> taken in his place. <hi>Everard</hi> hereupon grew enraged againſt his Grace, and took a moſt Helliſh reſolution, which was to Poyſon the Duke of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth,</hi> in reſolution ſo to do, as in apparances he came into <hi>England.</hi> Mr. <hi>Dalonſon</hi> being <hi>Everards</hi> intimate, he communicates unto Mr. <hi>Dalonſon</hi> his reſolution, to Poyſon, and did carry Mr. <hi>Dalonſon</hi> with him to buy the Poyſon for the ſaid purpoſe, and ſo did buy it. After that <hi>Dalonſon</hi> had fully penetrated into <hi>Everards</hi> mallgnity; Mr. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonſon</hi> giving me a viſit, he tells me, that he was ſo happy as to meet an opportunity and occaſion, which may demonſtrate unto me, that I had not oblieged an ungreatful Perſon, as unto the kind civility I did conferr upon him, and that he then came of purpoſe unto me; to diſcover unto me a very great concern, by which I may obliege a very great Perſon. Truly I am not of their humor who would not hear; It reſting in me after having heard, to give or take, ſo I asked Mr. <hi>Dalonſon</hi> what he would ſay, who tells me of <hi>Everards</hi> reſolution towards the Duke of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> and that he was with him when he bought the Poyſon, and that <hi>Everard</hi> was immediately reſolved to go for <hi>England</hi> to put his malignant Reſolution in Execution, telling me that <hi>Everard</hi> intended that an other Duke ſhould paſs the ſame path, which I do not now here name; at which I was not a little ſtartled, and conſidering upon the matter, I thanked Mr. <hi>Dalonſon</hi> for his good will, but told him that the diſcovery of that concern, was much fitter to have been communicated unto my Lord <hi>Locker;</hi> who was the Kings Embaſſador, and then in <hi>Paris</hi> Mr. <hi>Dalonſon</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies that he had a deſire to own his gratitude to me, beſides paying of his duty towards the Duke of <hi>Monmouths</hi> ſafety; and adds, that if ſo I did not give ear to him, and that any miſchief ſhould afterwards inſure, that I may repent. Upon this I asked Mr. <hi>Dalonſon,</hi> if he would go before good witneſs, atteſt the putting of this information into my hands, he ſaid he would and more then that; I preſently hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſent for witneſs, and amongſt others for young Mr. <hi>Lane</hi> my Lord <hi>Lansborow</hi> his Son, a fine civil underſtanding Gentleman, who is now here in Town, and ſince married unto my Lord of <hi>Northamptons</hi> Neece. Indeed Mr. <hi>Lane</hi> was very loth to meddle in the buſineſs, I telling him in Mr. <hi>Dalonſons</hi> preſence, what it was and how it was, which Mr. <hi>Lane</hi> at this day I dare ſay will ſay was thus, Mr. <hi>Dalonſon</hi> then ſaid that he would not only give it under his hand, and ſeal, but would as well go in perſon into <hi>England</hi> to maintain what he ſaid, and to confront <hi>Everard.</hi> Mr. <hi>Dalonſon</hi> did ſign and ſeal before wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſo I ſent it for <hi>England</hi> to thoſe it did concern, and in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular the Duke of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> and <hi>Dalonſon</hi> alſo told where <hi>Everard</hi> would or was to lodge in <hi>London,</hi> and doubted not that if he were
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99819:8"/> taken as he would deſcribe where, but that the ſaid Poyſon would be found with him; ſo <hi>Everard</hi> was ſeized upon and put into the Tower: <hi>Dalanſon</hi> did come into <hi>England,</hi> and confronted <hi>Everard</hi> before ſome Lords of the Council, <hi>Dalonſon</hi> was not ill looked upon for his infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, but had his paſs and a <hi>Viaticum</hi> to boot. So as viſibly its more probable that this put <hi>Everard</hi> into the Tower, rather then what he ſaith in his depoſitions, after <hi>Everards</hi> being confronted by <hi>Dalon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Everard</hi> was returned to the Tower, and <hi>Dalonſon</hi> left at his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. After <hi>Everards</hi> being in ſome cloſe reſtriction, then he fain would intimate unto Sir <hi>John Robinſon,</hi> ſome informations as tending to Plots as Priſoners in ſuch ſtraights ſeldom fail to foment; hoping thereby to procure themſelves ſome eaſe, yet would <hi>Everard</hi> have daſhed upon Sir <hi>John</hi> for not repreſenting or giving his ear; but out of doubt Sir <hi>John</hi> hath done the duty of his place; <hi>Everard</hi> in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions gives out that this <hi>Dalonſon</hi> was his man, a moſt palpable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth; I have known <hi>Everard</hi> a long time, but never in a condition to keep a man, but he ſtill was to be kept.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. My name being by <hi>Everards</hi> means introduc'd and traduc'd, it gives me ſcope to follow with a larger declaration in my ſufferance, my cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit being thus trampled upon, by Fobbs, Raſcals, and Villains, that never dar'ſt appear to lay any thing to my charge, face to face or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Juſtice, but ſtill like a Parator falſly informing behind my back, I am not the only thus ſerved, O what a pitty it is, that the noble Law which was allowed of to the Lord <hi>Rea,</hi> and <hi>David Ramſy</hi> ſhould not again be permitted; which was to fight <hi>Leſpee a la main</hi> on a publick ſtage, to maintain the Truth, which would give an Allaye un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to impoſtory and falſe accuſations. Is it not ſtrange as thus, that this <hi>Everard</hi> ſhould be ſo impudent as to have me ſummoned to the Houſe of Commons Bar, to make me appear, as I did there in <hi>May</hi> laſt 1679. and to referr unto what I ſhould witneſs, and ſuch as he names which can witneſs as now I do?</p>
            <p n="5">V. Maſter ſpeaker did ask me, if that in <hi>Paris 1673.</hi> that this <hi>Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard</hi> did not tell me that Troubles, Plots, Deſigns, and Diſturbances, were ingendring towards the prejudice of <hi>England,</hi> I anſwered in part he did, but that as unto particulars he did not, nor have I preſſed to know, I having notice from other manner of hands then his, that great engines were at work to prejudice His Moſt Excellent Majeſtie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſubverſion of his Laws and Government, and fomented to be upheld by greater perſons, then yet where named or ſpoken off. The ſpeaker asked me why I had not declared them, I replied it ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he knew not whether I had or not: I adding that if I had not done, what my duty and Loyalty oblieged me unto; that I would diſclaim in the leaſt Grace or Favor from the King, his moſt Honorable Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or Laws of the Land, ſo as I was ordered to withdraw, not doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but that I ſhould be ſummond to declare what I knew in thoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns, yet I was not, but in a day or two after, was ſummon'd to appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99819:9"/> the Committee of Secrecy, I did, and they looked on me, and I upon them, they ſaid they had no orders concerning me, ſo we par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. But had I been interrogated, ſure fear nor ſhame ſhould not keep me, from declaring the names of the intermedlers.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. It is in part wonderful that this <hi>Everard</hi> being ever bred a Papiſt, and begotly one as to my knowledge, he never would as much as read any Books of controverſy, often vowing that any Books that gave contradiction to the Roman Tenets, were Heretically, and ſo not to be read, and that this man without the concourſe with any Proteſtant Divine ſhould turn convert, muſt appear as a great bleſſing of God, or that it muſt be upon ſome worldly intereſt; and whereas he ſpeaks of his reconciliation to <hi>chalonton</hi> I doubt, it is that were he put to it, that he could not make out.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. I having not named the fomentors of theſe diſturbances, being not ſummoned thereunto, may not be of the ſame reſolution in my fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing deſcriptions. Sir <hi>Robert Walſh</hi> declares to the World, that he ever did and doth renounce the leſt of Grace, or Favor from His Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majeſty, His moſt Honorable Houſes of Parliamen or Laws, if any diſloyalty is or can be laid to his charge, yet is he and hath been Murthered alive, through falſe ſuggeſtions and informations, which none ever did or would appear to juſtifie againſt him, one was that in the Year 1655. or 1656. that he was imployed, by the then Uſurper <hi>Oliver Cronwel,</hi> and by then the Lord <hi>Brohill,</hi> now living Earl of <hi>Orery</hi> into <hi>Flanders</hi> to Kill His Moſt Sacred and Anointed King, and this fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented by Villains, Raſcals, and falſe Informers, who never did or durſt appear to lay any thing of that nature, or of any other crime unto his charge before Juſtice, though they were thereunto ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned, yet was Sir <hi>Robert</hi> made Priſoner, and his only Son in <hi>Brucels</hi> for 33. Months, ſtarving with cold and hunger; If ſuch as ſo aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sir <hi>Robert</hi> had appeared, he had coſts damage and intereſt againſt them, which they did not? Though ſummon'd thereunto, by <hi>Don John D' Auſtrea</hi> and the <hi>Marquis</hi> of <hi>Caraſſenas</hi> then Governors of <hi>Flanders,</hi> Sir <hi>Roberts</hi> damage would be more, then they could pay, though not as much as <hi>Dunkirk</hi> or <hi>Clarendon</hi> Houſe was ſold for.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. My Moſt Sacred King, being ever juſt in himſelf, was not willing that Sir <hi>Robert</hi> ſhould ſo ſuffer for want of Juſtice; ſo his Moſt Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Majeſty upon the ſollicitations, of many Nobles, ſtrangers and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of His Majeſty, was pleaſed to refer the concern unto the Judge Millitary of <hi>Flanders</hi> to determine, who certified unto His Moſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Majeſty, and His Catholick Majeſty, the injuſtice of Sir <hi>Roberts</hi> impriſonment, whereupon His Catholick Majeſty ſent his orders in theſe words, which is ſtill extant unto the Governors of <hi>Flanders,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing loth to find, that a Gentleman and a Perſon of Honor, ſhould ſo be Martyred under his Laws.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:99819:9"/>
            <p>The words of the Order were; to our Governors and Treaſurers in <hi>Flanders,</hi> ſet Sir <hi>Robert Walſh</hi> at liberty, and pay the coſts and charges of his Impriſonment out of our Treaſury. He being made Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner at the inſtigation of ſome of His Majeſty of Great Britains Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, <hi>(fine culpa)</hi> this Order coming, Sir <hi>Robert</hi> would not accept of his liberty, but by Order of his own King, ſo he did obtain, from that Moſt Honorable Perſon the Earl of <hi>Caſtlehaven</hi> who is now here, to carry the ſaid Order, unto His moſt Excellent Majeſty with an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deſire, that if any thing was or could be laid unto Sir <hi>Roberts</hi> charge, that it ſhould be put in againſt him. Sir <hi>Robert</hi> humbly praying His Majeſty then being in <hi>Bruxels,</hi> that any of His Majeſties Subjects <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, Iriſh,</hi> or <hi>Scotch,</hi> may be made his Judges, he moſt willingly owning that His Moſt Excellent Majeſties Power and Laws, may be of as full ſorce and value againſt him there; unto which he was as ready and willing to ſubmit himſelf, as now he is unto His Moſt Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Pleaſure.</p>
            <p n="10">X. Sir <hi>Robert</hi> at the inſtigation of <hi>Everard,</hi> being ſummon'd to the Bar of the Honorable Houſe of Commons, and having made his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavors to have diſcharged his duty as aforeſaid, yet did he petition the houſe, and put his petition into the hands of an Honorable mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the ſaid Houſe, to be preſented unto Mr. Speaker, which was ſo done by Sir <hi>John Coriton;</hi> who tells Sir <hi>Robert</hi> that the Speaker read every word thereof, as is hereunto Annexed, the Copy of the ſaid pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, I Sir <hi>Robert</hi> would not be afraid nor aſhamed, to have named the Ingenders, and Fomentors of the Troubles and diſturbances, to have been ſet on Foot towards His Majeſties Dominions, had he been ſammon'd thereunto; and is not backward to ſay that the Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Houſe of Commons, would not have been diſpleaſed to ſee, and order that ſome of the intermedlers may be detected and executed, no leſs would any good Subject of <hi>England.</hi> Pardon Noble Reader, if that I preſume to inmind that Criminals indiſloyalty ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Juſtice, ſuch as to them may be due; and I to be the firſt were I criminal therein, ſo I wiſh the ſame towards all or any Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects upon proofs, before their competent Adjudgers or Judges, that thereby criminals may receive indign and publick Puniſhment, and that Innocency may be protected and upheld. This tends unto Sir <hi>Robert Walſh</hi> ſufferances, who forgot as unto one of <hi>Everards</hi> depoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to make anſwer, as this, in particular he makes mention of one Mrs <hi>wingfield, alias Hampton,</hi> and forſooth, that his man <hi>Daliſon,</hi> he meaning <hi>Dalonſon,</hi> who never was his man or ſervant; and that he and Sir <hi>Robert Walſh</hi> did well know the ſaid Woman. Upon my Word and Honor, I never did know the ſaid Woman, never ſaw her direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, nor nover heard of ſuch a Woman, nor of her name until his now naming of her in his depoſitions: Pray Noble Readers, let no man think that I villifie this <hi>Everards</hi> evidence, as for the King if he pretends to give evidence; no I do not, nor would I intermeddle therein, or with any thing therein concerned, but what may daſh upon my own
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:99819:10"/> particular, which nature and the law of man cannot but allow to be juſtifiable, ſo as this gap opened unto me by <hi>Everard,</hi> putts me into a way of Juſtifying my ſelf to the world, being forced to declare my ſufferances. Under which I have ſo long groned, procured me by Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars, ſo as it may be ſaid, that Liars are the ſons of the Devil, and truth-tellers the Creatures of God.</p>
            <div type="petition">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Copy of Sir</hi> Robert Walſh <hi>his Petition unto the Honorable Houſe of Conpnons.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
               <p>That your Petitioner having lived moſt of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ime, for theſe Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Years paſt in the <hi>French</hi> Kings Territories, and ſince the Year 1669. particularly in <hi>Paris,</hi> until the Year 1675. Mr. <hi>Progers</hi> of his Majeſties Bed-Chamber, and heretofore a Member of this Honorable Houſe, was by His Majeſty's permiſſion ordered to keep a correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondence with your Petitioner, as unto what may relate unto his Majeſties Service, and the intereſts of his good Subjects, as may evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently be made to appear, unto any this Honorable Houſe may pleaſe to appoint, to hear the tranſactions and paſſages of the ſaid correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; who as accordingly may make report unto this Honorable Houſe, of the validity thereof. Your Petitioner alſo having given an account, in his Repreſentments unto ſome of His Majeſties Miniſters of State, which had they timely given ear unto, undoubtly muſt have conduced unto His Majeſties intereſt, and that of his good Subjects, but the averſneſs of ſome towards the giving of a juſt hearing, unto your Petitioners Repreſentments, hath Ecclipſed your Petitioner as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo his Repreſentments; by your Petitioners care and endeavors, he did ſo prevail with a perſon, who hath been above Twenty years under secretary in <hi>France,</hi> to the secretary of state, in the Tranſactions of the <hi>French</hi> concerns, yet he became diſcontented and was unſatisfied, and though he was well in Money, yet much would ambition more, ſo as your Petitioner prevailed with him to come hither in 1675. and the rather that in the ſurintendent <hi>Monſiere de Fouketts</hi> being great, this perſon was known unto His Moſt Excellent Majeſty, and came reſolved hither to give His Majeſty great Lights and intelligence, as regarding the Tranſactions of <hi>France.</hi> Here your Petitioner doth give a Brief which when proviſed, as alſo Mr. <hi>Progers</hi> Letters probably this Honorable Houſe may Judge, that this man's Repreſentments and Intelligence, would have proved of uſe, but ſome ill adviſers, who perhaps were here concerned, or that carried an animoſity againſt your Petitioner, did ſo deturn that his Repreſentments could not gain Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, elſe undoubtedly he would ſo have furniſhed againſt the <hi>French</hi> King, which would put water into his Wine, and have clipt his Wings, here annexed you read what your Petitioner could draw or gather out of him, which he Repreſented, where his Allegiance and duty did bind him to have done, and withal one of Mr. <hi>Progers</hi> his
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99819:10"/> Letters, your Petitioner in order thereunto comes into <hi>England</hi> being of the firſt, if not the firſt, who gave Lights and Intelligence of ill deſigns, and of a ſubverſion intended, towards the Government and Laws of this Kingdom, ſo as your Petitioner could have no ſiniſter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention.</p>
               <p>Though this <hi>Edmund Everard</hi> did moſt pernitiouſly and falſly ſay, before this Honorable Houſe, that your Petitioner in <hi>Paris,</hi> did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caution the Talbots from truſting this <hi>Everard,</hi> ſo as the malice of this <hi>Everard</hi> might have ſcandalouſly abuſed your Petitioner, who is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and willing to anſwer before this Honorable Houſe, diſclaiming in any grace or favor, if any diſloyalty could or can be laid to his charge, your Petitioner could look for no other but revenge from this <hi>Everard:</hi> for your Petitioner being the Perſon that procured <hi>Everards</hi> Impriſonment in the Tower, an action this Honorable Houſe would have allowed of, did they but know upon what occaſion and grounds, and how I was and am ready to maintain my acting therein, the Anixels ſome Years paſt were ſhewed unto ſome of the members of the Honorable Houſe, to the Lord <hi>Cavendiſh,</hi> Sir <hi>John Coryton,</hi> Sir <hi>Francis Winnington,</hi> and Sir <hi>John Earnly,</hi> many others, your Petitioner humbly prayeth that any of the members of this Honorable Houſe, may be ordered to ſee what your Petitioner can ſhow, as to hear what he hath to ſay for the good and intereſts of His Majeſty, and that of his good Subjects, and that in as much as that your Petitioner came into <hi>England</hi> of purpoſe, for the ſervice and intereſt as afore-ſaid, that according to the Report made by thoſe Commisſions, your Petitioner may find the effects of your Juſtice, and he ſhall Pray <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">I. My Repreſentments were given the Miniſters of State in the Year 1675. 1676. Theſe are what Repreſentments attended my Petition, that Sir <hi>John Coriton</hi> put into the hands of Maſter Speaker, Sir <hi>Robert</hi> in the Year 1675. brought with him out of <hi>France,</hi> the perſon men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in his Petition, firſt he would have made Evident, that there was then of His Majeſties Subjects a Caball in <hi>France,</hi> who were very active and buſie, being thereunto much incouraged by a great Perſon, to ingender great tumults and diſturbances in His Moſt Excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Kingdoms, who would have put into His Majeſties Hands, ſome Letters from their Correſpondence, writ from hence unto the ſaid Cabal in <hi>Paris,</hi> and ſome of theirs from <hi>Paris</hi> into their aſſociates here, and would have declared how they were introduced unto the <hi>French</hi> King, and his reception of them.</p>
               <p n="2">II. He would have diſcovered, that ſome perſons in <hi>England</hi> were gained by the <hi>French</hi> King, and his Miniſters to be of Intelligence with them, ſo as that thereby the <hi>French</hi> might have given the better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, unto their tranſactions with the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and that he would no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate ſome of thoſe of His Majeſties Subjects, who were ſo gained by the <hi>French</hi> King and Miniſters.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:99819:11"/>III. He would have made it apparent, that the great Preparations that the <hi>French</hi> King made for War, did bend to bring the States of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to His Majeſties Bent, which if he did not by force of Arms com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, he was ſure to do when he pleaſed to afford them plauſeable Terms, which-depended on His Majeſty to do when ever he pleaſed, and that once getting in the ſtates of <hi>Holland,</hi> the Confederates would ſoon come to tearms, and that once coming ſo, the <hi>French</hi> King tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Breath would ſoon imploy His Army Elſewhere, as this man would more particularly and probably into His Majeſties Kingdoms, declare here, had our Miniſters of ſtate given him a hearing, but he being not heard went very unſatisfied for <hi>Holland,</hi> where certainly he was liſtened unto, and gave great lights to the ſtates as unto the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of their Treaty, and accommodation with <hi>France.</hi> This man was not wanting in money, I may ſay he was very well to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, but diſatisfied in <hi>France,</hi> and being very knowing in the <hi>French</hi> concerns, he would thereby increaſe his Fortune.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. I could examplifie much upon what this man could have done, but as the times go it's more convenient not, when I could not be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced in gaining credit for this-mans repreſentments, I made them no Jewels, I communicating them unto many, and ſo were they by others to the <hi>French</hi> King, and his Miniſters from hence, ſo as if I went now for <hi>France,</hi> my reception would be but cold, I having I may with Juſtice ſay, that I was the firſt, that firſt gave notice of theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended revolutions and diſturbances, though I never hitherto did name the perſons who were firſt ſet on work to contribute unto the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing theſe Tumults, however I am not unſatisfied, to have contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by my endeavors towards the payment of my duty, unto my Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, and though the returns I meet with, are leading to deturn in the future, ſuch as may not reſolve to continue in the Principals of Loyalty which I do and ever ſhall, which time may give an undeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able demonſtration of. Two things I may aver; the firſt is, that I have no fear; ſecond, that I am not by any means diſcouraged, in perſiſting to do my Kings ſervice, as willingly as ever.</p>
               <p n="5">V. I have been an eye-witneſs, and active in the War of 1639. until 1646. Therefore I may give now I am in, ſome accounts in the ſaid War, when the ſaid War began, as my Fare hath rendered me ſubject unto Impriſonments, I was then ſo, and for the ſins and debts of my youth Priſoner in the King Bench. His Glorious Majeſty of Bleſſed Memory, and her Majeſty then quitted <hi>London,</hi> which I wiſh they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had, I was then Her Majeſties Sworn Servant, and but in extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary, I petitioned to the Houſe of Lords, that I might be ſet at liberty, as a priviledge that did belong unto Her Majeſties Servants; unto which the Lords conſented, and an Order was made for my Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, which ſtill ſtands upon record in the Houſe of Lords, and I then ſet at Liberty. It was no mean thought or concern, that invited
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99819:11"/> 
                  <hi>Edward</hi> Earl of <hi>Dorſet,</hi> the Lord Chamberlain to Her Majeſty, who was a Lord in deed, to uphold the priviledges belonging to Her Majeſty, he was my Advocate, nay Solliciter in my behalf and ſtuck to me, not by ſaying, I will do you all the Service that lyes in my power, but in the performance to act what he ſaid or promiſed: I was by the Order of the Houſe of Lords diſcharged from Priſon, yet in the year 61 returning into <hi>England</hi> was again taken for the old Debt, and made Priſoner; but my Lord was dead, that Noble <hi>Dorſet,</hi> elſe aſſuredly there had been payed as much duty unto her Majeſties Priviledges as before, ſhe then being here preſent as was in her abſence, as in my concern, but the times are chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and we too much a La mode, ſome promiſes much, and in effect per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form little, this is no romance and leſs is, what will follow: The wars beginning then; truly I was offerd by the Houſes of Parliament a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Imployment, my Tenent not leading me that way, I quietly got away, and went for <hi>York</hi> where my King was; and I in no ill equipage, and after kiſſing his hand, applyed my ſelf unto the Lord <hi>Henry Wilmot</hi> late Earl of <hi>Rocheſter</hi> deceaſed, who left this Young Lord, I hope to inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit the Fathers Worth and Gallantry. The Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> was then raiſing a Regiment of Horſe for His Majeſty, and aſſoon as I came to him, he did embrace me, bidding me welcome, not Alamode but in effect, telling me I ſhould command his own Troop, then a raiſing, ſo I did, and in it a Hundred Valiant brave men, moſt Gentlemen of Eſtate and Quality, who not long after did ſo approve themſelves, who could not chooſe but ſo to do, having ſuch a General in the head of them as was his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, what hath not he done to leave his Name Renowned.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. I being made Priſoner laſt Parliament 1678. all my Papers and Writings ſeized upon, and I carried Priſoner to the Black Rod by Sir <hi>Edward Cartred,</hi> who was very civil towards me, and carried before the Moſt Honorable Committee of Lords, and yet the Noble Lord that moved againſt me in Parliament, appeared no more to have made party againſt me, believing not as I preſume what was told him.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. Now give me leave Noble Readers, to give a relation of the firſt War betwixt King and Parliament, which truly is uncontradict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, for it ſhall carry nothing in it but a real Character of truth. At the Battle of Edge-hill, His Highneſs Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> that ever Renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Perſon, Commanded the right Wing of our Horſe, who put the Enemies into an abſolute rout, and the Earl of <hi>Brandford</hi> the left, unto whoſe ſhare it came to charge the Enemies right Wing, His Highneſs putting into a derout their left Wing, the Battle begun upon a Sunday Morning, and the Lord <hi>Digby</hi> commanded our reſerve of Horſe, who gave more Teſtimony of his Courage then of conduct, but that never to be buried in oblivion the deceaſed Earl of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> this Lord being then Commiſſary General of the Horſe, and in the head of our left Wing of Horſe, and in the head of his one Troop, Commanded by Sir <hi>Robert Walſh,</hi> and his Lordſhips Troop conſiſting of at leaſt a Hundred Brave and Noble Gentlemen, as Sir <hi>John Dongan,</hi> Sir <hi>Brien</hi> O <hi>Neale,</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:99819:12"/> Sir <hi>Henry Talbot,</hi> sir <hi>walter Dongan, ſon</hi> to sir <hi>John,</hi> brave <hi>Iriſh</hi> Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, whoſe moſt Valiant deportment gave great Teſtimony of their Loyalty, as I may ſay did the whole Troop and his Regiment, as may witneſs that firſt ſervice they were in, his Royal Majeſty of Bleſſed Memory, and His now sacred Majeſty, and his Royal Highneſs. were not only there as witneſs of their Loyal subjects, but alſo hazardly and dangerouſly ingaged in the ſaid Battle, to their great and ever Renowned Everlaſting Glory. The Lord <hi>wilmos</hi> having charged the right Wing of the Enemy, did beat them and put them ſo in diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as that they run confuſedly into <hi>Kington,</hi> which was in the Rear of their Army, the reſerve of our Horſe unpremeditatedly follow the purſuit of the Enemy, which gave the advantage unto the reſerve of the Enemies Horſe, as alſo unto their main Body, that they fell upon that Renowned Moſt Honorable Earl of <hi>Linzy</hi> our General, and ſo furiouſly, as that His Majeſties own Regiment was diſordered, and divers of their ſtandards taken at the ſame time, where the Noble Lord <hi>Gerard</hi> Commanding Three Regiments of Foot made a moſt manly ſtand, our Horſe being for the moſt part mingled in the Enemies, and his Highneſs Prince <hi>Ruperts</hi> Horſe purſuing, fortune proved ſo favor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able unto sir <hi>Robert walſh,</hi> as to keep the Lord <hi>Wilmots</hi> Troop in a Body unſcattered, ſo as he encountred ſome of the Horſe that charged the Earl of <hi>Linzy</hi> in their return, this being in the rear of the Enemies Army towards the Town of <hi>Kington,</hi> sir <hi>Robert</hi> with his Troop charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them and recovered the ſtandards, which they took from the Kings Regiment, and alſo took ſome of the Enemies, and sir <hi>Robert</hi> being then in the rear of the Enemies Army in the Town of <hi>Kington,</hi> did ſieze upon Two Pieces of Cannon and a Waggon, brought them into the rear of His Majeſties Army. His Glorious Majeſty having lain that night upon the top of Edge-Hill, his Army not then drawn from the Enemies, sir <hi>Robert</hi> towards Morning brought the Two Pieces of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non and Waggon to the bottom of Edge-hill, and brought the ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard of His Majeſties, and ſome of the Enemies unto His Highneſs Prince <hi>Rupert,</hi> who immediately did preſent them, and sir <hi>Robert</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to His Majeſty, who was graciouſly pleaſed, there to Knight sir <hi>Robert</hi> for the acceptable ſervice he then did render.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. Some time after, his then Royal Highneſs the Prince, going to command in the Weſt of <hi>England,</hi> Sir <hi>Robert</hi> was by His Majeſty Ordered into the Weſt, to ſerve under his Royal Highneſs Bannor, which he did, as Lieutenant Collonel of Sir <hi>George Vaughans</hi> Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Horſe, who was a brave Worthy Noble Gentleman, and then Sheriff of <hi>wiltſhire,</hi> leaving all to Sir <hi>Robert,</hi> Conduct: But he ſtill came when any fight was. The Deviſes being then ſurrounded by Sir <hi>william waller,</hi> and all our Army in the Deviſes, which were ſo ſhort of Ammunition and Match, that they were forced to make uſe of all the Bed-cords which were in the Town for Match. His Royal Highneſs Prince <hi>Maurica,</hi> that Renowned Prince, the Famous and Honourable the Lord Marqueſs of <hi>Herford,</hi> and the Honourable
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:99819:12"/> Lord <hi>Hopson</hi> were in the Deviſes, and Sir <hi>william waller</hi> ſurrounded them with his Horſe, Foot, and Cannon, having ſummoned the Trained-Bands of thoſe parts to come and joyn with him, which they then did, the Prince and Lords called then in the Deviſes a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of War, and concluded that their beſt expedient was to diſpatch an Officer, that would hazard to get to <hi>Oxford,</hi> to give His Majeſty advice how it ſtood with them in the Deviſes, whereupon did depend very highly His Majeſties Intereſt: They pitched upon Sir <hi>Robert walſh</hi> to go, and ſent for him, he being with his Regiment upon the Out-guards, and asked him if that he would adventure; he made anſwer that he would moſt willingly and readily; that he regarded no hazard, or danger, ſo as that he could but compaſs their Relief: upon which he was immediately ordered to go, which he did, being not ill Horſed, and went all alone, carrying not a ſervant or mart with him. He was in his way cloſely purſued by the Enemies Scouts, and part of their Out-guards; but it pleaſed God he got ſafe, and the next morning got to His Majeſty, who their was in <hi>Oxford.</hi> His Majeſty did then immediately Order that Relief ſhould preſently be ſent, and calling upon the Lord <hi>wilmot,</hi> did order, without delay, that he ſhould get ready the Horſe, and march unto the Relief of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſes, which was as ſoon as poſſibly obſerved; ſo as the Lord <hi>wilmot,</hi> the Lord <hi>Biron,</hi> Colonel <hi>Thomas weſton</hi> now Earl of <hi>Newport,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of the beſt Commanders did march, and hardly drew Bit in their march to the Deviſes, which was no eaſie or ſhort march: And when arrived at the Deviſes, the Horſe were weary, and I may ſay by she ſame; and ſtragling, that we miſſed Five hundered Horſe of our Number coming from <hi>Oxford.</hi> My Lord <hi>wilmot</hi> from <hi>Malborough</hi> did diſpatch Sir <hi>Robert walſh,</hi> all alone towards the devices with Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to return aſſoon as poſſible, to bring him notice how matters went, Sir <hi>Robert</hi> did go and return quickly to my Lord, whoſe conduct and Carriage was ſo evidently, made apparant to the world, as nothing could be more; my Lords; (as thus) His Highneſs Prince <hi>Maurite,</hi> and she Lord <hi>Hopton</hi> did march with the Horſe out of the devices, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to have joyned to the Lord <hi>wilmot,</hi> and in part did, his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Horſe were not many, and when he came to joyn, they adviſed in Council, what was to be done, <hi>waller</hi> and his Army, Horſe, cannon and Foot and Train-Bands very numerous, and our Horſe were weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed being not above Fifteen Hundred or Two Thouſand, at the Council the Lord <hi>wilmot</hi> gave his opinion as thus; that his Horſe were all weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and by conſequence an impoſſibility that they could make any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat, from the Enemy without being utterly cut off. The Enemies Army being not half a Mile from them, and therefore if the Prince and the Lord <hi>Hopton</hi> pleaſed to conſent, that he would advance with a Thouſand Horſe, to the top of a Hill which lay betwixt them, and the Enemy, preſuming that the Enemy would ſo undervalue them, as that they would march up the Hill to devour them. My Lord <hi>wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mot</hi> adding, that if they ſo would come as they did, perhaps it might ruin them, which did, the Princes and Lord <hi>Hopton</hi> did conclude with
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99819:13"/> the Lord <hi>wilmots</hi> ſenſe, whereupon of the Horſe which were in the devices, my Lord <hi>wilmot</hi> of the Weſtern Horſe only takes Sir <hi>John Digby,</hi> a moſt Noble and brave Officer, and Sir <hi>Robert Walſh,</hi> with their Troops to joyn with him, my Lord ſends Lievtenant Collonel <hi>Paul Smith,</hi> who was unto his Lordſhips Regiment with a Hundred Horſe as a forlorn hope, and marches himſelf in the right Wing of a party of his Horſe, and adjoyns Sir <hi>John Digby,</hi> and Sir <hi>Robert Walſh</hi> with their Troops, to be at the head of his ſecond Diviſion of his left Wing, and his Highneſs Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> marched with the Body of the Horſe, it fell out ſo as my Lord <hi>Wilmet</hi> did Prognoſticate Sir <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Waller</hi> Orders Sir <hi>Arthur Haſelrick,</hi> to march up ſuch a Hill to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the Enemy, which he undertook in the Head of a Thouſand Horſe firſt, which were Armed <hi>Cap a pe,</hi> and afterwards named <hi>Lob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. Haſelrick</hi> ſending his forlorn hope, which was encountred by ours, he marched in the head of two diviſions, and the reſt of his Horſe marching in Regiments up the Hill after one another, which were between Four and Five Thouſand Horſe. The Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived their charge, then charges them, beats <hi>Haſelrick,</hi> and <hi>Haſelrick</hi> diſorders the reſt of his Horſe, the Prince and Lord <hi>Hopton</hi> advance, ſo as the Enemies Horſe was clean forced to run away. Then the Prince and Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> conſults to charge their Foot and Cannon, which they put in Execution and did Rout them, took all their Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, Foot and Colors, e're that our Foot in the devices could get out to joyn with us, this was ſo clear and fair a Victory, as that it gained his Majeſty the whole Weſt of <hi>England,</hi> which then was of the laſt conſequence; The Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> then calls Sir <hi>Robert Walſh,</hi> and ſays that as he went to His Majeſty to bring this relief, he ſhould imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly poſt to His Majeſty and give him the account, which Sir <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> did, His Majeſty being not at <hi>Oxford,</hi> but gone to meet Her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty then come out of <hi>Holland,</hi> which he met at Edge-Hill where Sir <hi>Robert</hi> addreſt, and His Majeſty and Her Majeſty in the Coach, Sir <hi>Robert</hi> gave His Majeſty the account, which was moſt mightily accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and his Highneſs Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> and my Lord of St. <hi>Albans</hi> then by when Sir <hi>Robert</hi> gave the ccount, ſome time after the Lord <hi>Hopton</hi> retiring, his Brigade of Horſe was given Sir <hi>Robert Walſh,</hi> who was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo made Commiſſary General in the Weſt of Horſe and Foot, a charge of great truſt and Honor, as alſo of the Counties of <hi>Southampton, Suſſex, Surry</hi> and <hi>Kent,</hi> which then were aſſociated Counties, his Commiſſions are now extant, which were ſo ample and ſpatiouſly large, as that the General the Lord <hi>Goring</hi> was not over pleaſed, yet ſigned the Commiſſions. His Majeſty of Bleſſed Memory, gives Sir <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Walſh</hi> Commiſſion, to go for <hi>Ireland</hi> in the Year 1644. to raiſe Horſe and Foot, and in His Majeſties one hand, writes to my Lord of <hi>Ormond</hi> then Lord Lievtenant of Ireland, to give Sir <hi>Robert</hi> all aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and countenance, which that moſt ever Loyal untainted and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable Subject, did moſt willingly countenance Sir <hi>Robert</hi> in, giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all furtherance, ſo as Sir <hi>Robert</hi> did bring upon his own coſt and charge, without having a Peny from His Majeſty bring then out of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99819:13"/> 
                  <hi>Ireland</hi> a Hundred Horſe, which he recruted his Regiment with and His Glorious Majeſty being then in <hi>Cornewal</hi> to oppoſe <hi>Eſſex,</hi> who then was General. <hi>Liſtedel</hi> Caſtle was ſurrounded by <hi>Eſſex,</hi> his forces, <hi>Eſſex</hi> Lying of <hi>Liſtedell</hi> ſide, and His Majeſties Army of the other ſide of a ſmall River. Sir <hi>James Smith</hi> that Worthy Noble brave Gentleman, being ſent with his Regiment of Horſe For the Guard of the ſaid Caſtle, did there moſt Worthy ſervice and received cruel Wounds: Sir <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Walſh</hi> and his Brigade of Horſe were then commanded unto Sir <hi>James</hi> his relief, whoſe fate was ſo proſperous, in the beating of <hi>Eſſex</hi> his Foot from the Hedges about the ſaid Caſtle, and in view of His Majeſty and Army, that His Majeſty after Sir <hi>Roberts</hi> coming off, ſent for him, and took him by the hand, his Royal Highneſs then next His Majeſty, ſaying, he hoped to live to gratifie Sir <hi>Robert,</hi> not only for the ſervice he then ſaw him render, but as well for his Loyalty and former ſervices.</p>
               <p n="9">IX. Some time after the Lord <hi>Wilmots</hi> Impriſonment and confine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into <hi>Exeter,</hi> by the falſe reports of ſome, Sir <hi>Robert</hi> having been a Creature of the Lord <hi>Wilmots</hi> and his Officer, who moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly well knew his Loyalty, faithfulneſs and Gallantry, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly in His Majeſties ſervice, ſeeing the Lord <hi>Wilmots</hi> unjuſt diſgrace, being ſiezed upon in the head of the Army by Mr. <hi>Thomas Elliot;</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which Sir <hi>Robert</hi> was ſurrendring and giving up his Imployment and charge; His Majeſty taking notice of which, the Army then march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, His Majeſty ſtopt, and ſo did the Army, and called upon Sir <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> ſaying, he heard that he was upon quitting his ſervice, Sir <hi>Robert</hi> humbly replied, that he hoped that His Majeſty would permit him ſo to do, ſeeing that the Lord <hi>Wilmot,</hi> whoſe Loyalty and ſervice he ever was a witneſs of, was ſo uſed, and truly Sir <hi>Robert</hi> did plainly ſo declare his unwillingneſs to ſerve any longer; His Majeſty was pleaſed to give Sir <hi>Robert</hi> great encouragement to continue, and in an extraordinary manner, and told him that he ſhould not quit, and that he commanded him not to quit, unto which there reſted no anſwer, (but obedience) the world ignores not with what ungrounded falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood the Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> was then made Priſoner, and how he came off with honor. Then His Majeſty came into <hi>Wiltſhiere,</hi> and came to <hi>Andover</hi> where Sir <hi>William Wallers</hi> Army lay near, <hi>Waller</hi> ſent a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable party of Horſe to obſerve His Majeſties Army, whereupon the Lord <hi>George Goring,</hi> that Worthy Commander then General of his Royal Highneſs's Army, immediately did order to draw out a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable party of Horſe, and did Order Sir <hi>Robert Walſh</hi> to command the ſaid Party, with order to purſue Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> which readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was put in Execution, where many Voluntiers readily went along, and particularly then Mr. <hi>Henry Bennet</hi> now Earl of <hi>Arlington,</hi> with ſo much of good will and reſolution as none could demonſtrate more Sir <hi>Robert</hi> then deſiring him not to go, he being a perſon who was then in the Pen charge and Imployment, and ſo readily kind and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to ſerve and obliege us Officers, ſo as that if any thing ſhould hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99819:14"/> him, it would infinitely redown to our loſs and ſufferance, but he would not be deturned, of bearing a ſhare in that occaſion, which was ſo viſibly near of being put in Execution; in the purſuance of which, he then from the Enemy did receive that Noble ſcar of honor, which to this day he beareth the mark of in his Face, which aſſoon as Sir <hi>Robert</hi> ſaw, he immediately did Order Collonel <hi>Garret Moor,</hi> now here in Town to conduct him off; and to have him to the Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion to be dreſſed, which accordingly was done.</p>
               <p n="10">X. Some time after the Army was given up in <hi>Corn-wall,</hi> and Moſt Officers to ſhift for themſelves, of which number Sir <hi>Robert</hi> being one, he betook himſelf for <hi>Ireland,</hi> and there treated with the <hi>French</hi> Kings Envoy, by name <hi>Monſieur de la Monnerie,</hi> for Sir <hi>Robert</hi> to carry a Regiment of Foot into the <hi>French</hi> Kings ſervice, who capitulated with Sir <hi>Robert</hi> in the Name of His Chriſtian Majeſty: that Sir <hi>Robert</hi> upon his Landing in <hi>France</hi> ſhould receive Thirty Crowns, for each man, and ſhould have a penſion of Two Thouſand Crowns yearly, beſides other great and large promiſes in words, which never were perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Sir <hi>Robert</hi> upon his one coſts and charge, hired Two great <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> Ships, into which he Shipped Nine Hundred and Fifty men, from the County of <hi>Galway,</hi> and the City of <hi>Galway,</hi> and ſailing for <hi>France</hi> was met by ſome Parliament Ships, who took one of Sir <hi>Roberts</hi> Ships, loden with men, which they ſent into the iſlands, but fortune fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voring the Ship that Sir <hi>Robert</hi> was in, did eſcape, and he got into <hi>Haver de Grace</hi> with Six Hundred men, he ſerved the <hi>French</hi> King as Collonel of the ſaid men, which Agent <hi>la Monnerie</hi> did not perform his capitulation in a Tittle; ſo as Sir <hi>Robert</hi> grew unſatisfied in His Majeſties Service, and looſing his Sons who were Captains in Sir <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berts</hi> ſaid Regiment: then the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> taking Arms againſt his King, Sir <hi>Robert</hi> took his diſmiſs and paſſe from the King, and gave himſelf into the ſervice of the Prince of <hi>Conde.</hi> After ſome time Sir <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> was taken Priſoner and put into the <hi>Baſtill,</hi> where he was forced to lye for Three Years, notwithſtanding that, the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> did uſe all indeavors to have Sir <hi>Robert</hi> exchanged, and did offer one <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur Bougy,</hi> for to Exchange Sir <hi>Robert;</hi> who was Lievtenant General in his Chriſtian Majeſties Army, which was denied, it being given out, that Sir <hi>Robert</hi> did intend to kill Cardinal <hi>Mazarine,</hi> the ordinary common pretext, that when envy or malice contrives againſt man; then uſually its babbled and given out, that he was to kill the Prince or Miniſter of State.</p>
               <p n="11">XI. If gratitude were in practice, ſure Cardinal <hi>Mazarine</hi> would not have forgot his parts as hereunto; for when the Cardinal er'e he made his eſcape from <hi>Paris,</hi> was in very great apprehenſion and fear of his life by the Duke of <hi>Orleans,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Conde Monſieur de Beauford</hi> &amp; their party. Sir <hi>Robert</hi> having not then quit the Kings Service nor the court party, the Cardinal being in great apprehenſion of looſing his life, though he lodged in the Pallas Royal, though Sir <hi>Robert</hi> was then ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:99819:14"/> unſatisfied; he did remaſs and gather a Hundred Gentlemen, every one with his Sword and Piſtol, and had them into the Inns and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baretts in the <hi>Reu de bones enfents</hi> and near the Pallas Royal, and the Cardinal then being in hourly fear of being attacked in the Pallas. Sir <hi>Robert</hi> writ unto his Eminence, that he lay with a hundred Cavaliers, in Caſe that any attempt were made upon his Eminence: That Sir <hi>Robert</hi> was ready to be in the head of the ſaid Gentlemen to hazard his Life and theirs in the defence of his Eminence; who then ſent <hi>Monſieur de Navaile,</hi> now Duke <hi>de Navaile,</hi> to ſee if what Sir <hi>Robert</hi> writ was ſo; <hi>Monſieur de Navaile</hi> did to the Cardinal return, and certified him, that what Sir <hi>Robert</hi> writ to him was ſo. Upon which the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal, the Alarum being paſt, Two or Three days after, Sir <hi>Robert</hi> being in the Palſas Royal, the Cardinal took him in his Arms, ſaying he was a true Perſon of Honor; and that if ever it came in his way, that he never would forget Sir <hi>Roberts</hi> generoſity and kindneſs. But the Cardinal made it his profeſſion, not to be a ſlave to his word; yet did Sir <hi>Robert</hi> when he lay in the Baſtile, put him in mind of his promiſe, which proved one <hi>a la mode de France:</hi> But at long run, Mr. <hi>Walter Montegue</hi> a Perſon of Credit and Renown with the <hi>French</hi> Court, and Cardinal, was ſo honourable as to imploy himſelf for Sir <hi>Roberts</hi> liberty, which in fine he obtained; but upon ſuch Terms as have rarely been impoſed upon any Officer or Soldier of Fortune, which was thus; that Sir <hi>Robert Walſh</hi> ſhould put in Two Collonels of the Kings Army, and Two good Burgeſſes of <hi>Paris,</hi> who ſhould become bound in Fifty thouſand Crowns. That Sir <hi>Robert Walſh</hi> ſhould not ſerve nor carry Arms againſt His Chriſtian Majeſty in Five years fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, which was given by Sir <hi>Robert</hi> and performed. The Lord of <hi>Muskery,</hi> and Sir <hi>James Dillon</hi> were the Two Collonels who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came bound, <hi>Monſieur de Couteure,</hi> and <hi>Monſieur de la Coſte</hi> the Burgeſſes, and ſo Sir <hi>Robert</hi> was ſet at liberty. Could it be thought that ſo great a King would ſo far conſider a ſingle Officer, or Soldier of Fortune: I cannot but ſpeak well of the Prince of <hi>Conde;</hi> for when he firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived me into his Protection, ſeeing my Diſmiſs and Paſs from His Chriſtian Majeſty, he did afford me his Favour and Countenance, and when firſt I came to him, the Armies then lying about <hi>Villneufe</hi> St. <hi>George</hi> a little above <hi>Shallonton,</hi> the Kings Army lying of one ſide the River, Commanded by Mounſieur <hi>de Turene,</hi> and the Princes Army of <hi>Chalonton</hi> ſide. The Prince bid me take Five hundred Horſe and beat about <hi>Paris,</hi> to find ſome Booty which may put me into an Equipage; and that he would but moderately hear any Complaint that ſhould come againſt me. I did take the ſaid Horſe which were all <hi>Germans;</hi> and truly I did more ſtudy to render the Prince ſervice than to plunder, if it came not in my way; and ſo I marched all Night, and paſt by the Rear of the Kings Army, and took ſome Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Priſoners; my intent being to go to <hi>Pontoiſe</hi> to beat up ſome of the Kings Army who lay there; and in my return the next Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I drew up to refreſh betwixt St. <hi>Germans</hi> and St. <hi>Clow</hi> a top of a Hill: While I was there, I ſaw a Coach with ſix Horſes going for
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99819:15"/> 
                  <hi>Paris,</hi> I ſent a Party of my <hi>Germains</hi> to bring me that Coach, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to make a prize thereof; but who ſhould be in it but the beſt of men; ſo the <hi>Germains</hi> were greedy, and would underſtand no <hi>French</hi> or <hi>Engliſh;</hi> but one of his Lords, that noble Lord <hi>Garret</hi> as I take it; comes up to the party, and found me in the head of them, he ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me who commanded the party; I anſwered, he was not far off; then he tells me who was in the Coach, and made Priſoner. Upon which I immediately drew my Party towards the Coach, and waited on it to <hi>Paris.</hi> I am glad it was no other than his Subject that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Party. The Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> then being not very affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionate; the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> being ſlacken'd and I well ſatisfied in all occaſions, which may demonſtrate the paying of my duty and Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty; yet I was not a little ſatisfied, it was I that Commanded that Party, which prevented further trouble to the ſaid Coach. The Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> not being ignorant how the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> was gained to have proved ſlow in the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi>'s then pretenſions, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which the <hi>French</hi> King might have run the hazard <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">XII. Fortune was to me ſo favourable, that at the Battle of St. <hi>Antoine;</hi> I gained ſo much the heart of the Citizens of <hi>Paris,</hi> as that ever af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, they hardly would ſtir out of the Gates of <hi>Paris,</hi> without hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me in the head of them, as I was at St. <hi>Dennis,</hi> when <hi>Monſieur de Semegrine</hi> Commanding the Queens Guards, charged the <hi>Pariſiens</hi> and was repulſed, theſe troubles of <hi>Paris</hi> being appeaſed by the Prince of <hi>Condes</hi> quitting <hi>Paris,</hi> wherein he quit his chiefeſt hold: I betook my ſelf for <hi>Flanders,</hi> and made my addreſs unto his Grace the Duke of <hi>Ormond,</hi> who moſt kindly not degenerating from his ever wonted greatneſs and goodneſs, did afford me his Countenance; ſo as I by His Majeſties Order and Conſent, did venture for <hi>England,</hi> in hopes to prove uſeful for His Majeſties Rights and Intereſts. Upon which his Grace the Duke of <hi>Ormond</hi> writ unto me all in his own hand; that I ſhould come for <hi>England;</hi> and to advance my Intereſt and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours as in all I could for His Majeſties ſervice; aſſuring me; that if I could attain to be permitted by the Uſurper to be in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don;</hi> if ſo I ſhould ſometimes tranſgreſs in my expreſſions, towards His Majeſty, that it ſhould not in the future prejudice my Loyalty: Upon this I came for <hi>London,</hi> and did uſe all my endeavours to come in <hi>Thurloes</hi> favour, then Secretary to the Uſurper; I did ſo obtain from <hi>Thurloe,</hi> that he gave me his word, I ſhould have the liberty of the Town. I giving him my word that I would not act any thing againſt the State, during my being under their Government: So for a Months time I had acceſs unto <hi>Thurloe;</hi> but ſoon after; though I had <hi>Thurloe</hi>'s word for my liberty, that word was not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, but I was ſurprized, I lodging at one <hi>Elkings</hi> Houſe, who was a Packer and an <hi>Anabaptiſt,</hi> then dwelling in <hi>Mark-lune;</hi> and I preſume lives their ſtill. I was by Four Files of Musketeers ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized in my Bed, Captain <hi>William Bower</hi> then lying with me, and hurried away into the Tower, where I lay Four Months cloſe Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:99819:15"/> none being admitted to me but my Keeper; ſoon after was that moſt Noble and ever Renowned Earl of <hi>Orery,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Tennet,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Norwich</hi> the Earl of <hi>Clanricarde,</hi> and many Perſons of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity brought in Priſoners, and as I take it the only then made cloſe Priſoners, was that Famous never to be buried in Oblivion, the Duke of <hi>Albemarle</hi> and I cloſe Priſoner, ſome who then attended His Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majeſty did aſſuredly give the Uſurper notice, that I was in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> as imployed by my King, ſome time after, the liberty of the Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er being granted me, upon the interceſſion of <hi>Baxters</hi> Wife to her Husband. The Lord <hi>Brohil</hi> now Earl of <hi>Orery,</hi> who is a Perſon of that Honor, as will own what I here ſay, through the Interceſſion of his Honorable Siſter, then in <hi>London</hi> the Counteſs of <hi>Barimore,</hi> his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip did interpoſe for my liberty: Whereupon his Lordſhip came to the Tower, and gave me a viſit, his words as near as I can remember were theſe: Sir <hi>Robert</hi> had you ſerved the State, and his Highneſs the Protector as you did the King, what poſt or poſture do you imagine you might now be in, I ſeemingly did aver what his Lordſhip ſaid, why then ſaid my Lord can you now reſolve to ſerve his Highneſs, if you can I will tell you how, and you ſhall have your Liberty and Money to boot, unto which I did ſeem to liſten, then ſaid my Lord, you ſee what a deal of Noble-men and Gentlemen lye here Priſoners, and I will tell you upon what account. It is upon an intelligence we have received, that his Highneſs Perſon is to be attempted, and we fain would ſink into a diſcovery therein, and here be Two Perſons of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity now Priſoners, who make offer of their attempt, as unto what I intend to propoſe unto you, each of them now offering, that they will find out to make the diſcovery, but as I am inclined to get you your liberty, I have propounded to his Highneſs that you may be the Perſon imployed, and he hath conſented thereunto If ſo you can make it appear that you may be received at <hi>Bridges?</hi> and that upon your word and honor unto me, that you will really imploy your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavors to make the diſcovery, how his Highneſs Perſon was deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be attempted, and you ſhall have your liberty, and ſome Money for your Voyage. I replied that I firſt would addreſs unto the Duke of <hi>Ormond,</hi> to ſee if I could make my peace, and be admitted to Court, which my Lord <hi>Brohill</hi> gave me ſome time to do. And then I writ to the ſame tenure unto his Grace of <hi>Ormond,</hi> and an other Letter in private, unto his Grace of what paſt and was to paſs, and upon what termes I was to obtain my liberty, I ſhowing the return to the Lord <hi>Brohil,</hi> he procured me my liberty, &amp; Fifty or Sixty pound, upon my word I know not which; upon the Faith of a Chriſtian this was all, that paſt betwixt my Lord of <hi>Orery</hi> and me, or from any other of the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpers Creatures; I never having ſpoke to the Uſurper, only once he Landing at White-Hall-ſtaires, out of a Pair of Oares coming from <hi>Lambert,</hi> and I entring into a Pair of Oars, he asked who I was and called me to him, asked me whether the Iſland near <hi>Waterford</hi> was not mine, I ſaid of right it was, but that his Highneſs did take it from me and gave it Collonel <hi>Vernon,</hi> who had been his quarter Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:99819:16"/> General, ſo parted, and I never ſaw him ſince. As unto my Lord of <hi>Orery,</hi> I would take the Sacrament that he never ſpoke one word or ſyllable unto me of my King in the whole courſe of our tranſaction, but as heretofore I have mentioned, ſoon after I Landed in <hi>Flanders</hi> and went to <hi>Gant,</hi> there was caſually his Grace of <hi>Ormond,</hi> unto whom I preſently made my addreſs, but he being buſie with the Lord <hi>Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pepper,</hi> that time was not convenient; the next day I waited on his Grace, to give him the account of my Tranſactions in <hi>England,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting all I could gather, only that I would make it out, how ſome near His Majeſty did betray his Secrets, unto the Uſurper and his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, I offering upon pain of the loſs of my Head to give evident proofs of the ſaid intelligence. My Lord ſaid, he would give his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty who was then in <hi>Bruges</hi> an account of what I ſaid; ſome Two days after the Earl of <hi>Clancarthy,</hi> came to <hi>Gant</hi> from his Grace of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi> and brought me this meſſage, that it was His Majeſties Pleaſure, that I ſhould appear before His Majeſty and Council to anſwer what was to be laid to my charge, unto which I replied, that I was ready to appear, and the next day I being going into the Boat from <hi>Gant</hi> to <hi>Bruges,</hi> in obedience as I conceived to His Majeſties Pleaſure, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived an other meſſage from his Grace, that I ſhould immediatly leave the low Countries, by His Majeſties poſitive Order ſo expreſſed; or that I ſhould run the hazard of what ſhould follow. I anſwered I would in all things obey my Kings Command, though I well know that this Order was procured, by thoſe who knew themſelves guilty, how I would have accuſed them of their keeping intelligence with the Uſurper. Next day from <hi>Gant</hi> I took my journey towards <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> to get unto his Highneſs Prince <hi>Rupert,</hi> and took the City of <hi>Bruxels</hi> in my way, which was not much out of it, the Lord <hi>Digby</hi> and Sir <hi>Edward Hyde</hi> were then hand and glove, the world hath ſeen what they have been afterwards. Truly I was at a defiance with ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo as the true liberty of the Subject had been allowed me, for I neither would creep, or cringe to either: the Lord <hi>Digby</hi> was then immediatly by Sir <hi>Edward Hyde</hi> diſpatched, and Imployed after me to <hi>Bruxels,</hi> it being well known that I had entrance ſo with the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> who was then in <hi>Bruxels,</hi> ſo as to bring me to his Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Majeſties State Miniſters, and Governors there; where I would have declared of the Treacheries, done to my King; but the Lord <hi>Digby</hi> and Sir <hi>Edward Hydes</hi> joyning their heads, ſo contrived, that the Governors <hi>Don John d' Auſtrea</hi> and <hi>Marquis de Caraſſenas,</hi> were inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and poſſeſſed, that I was then imployed by the Uſurper, and Earl of <hi>Orery</hi> to Kill my King, ſo the next Morning after my arrival in <hi>Bruxels,</hi> my Son and Servant and I ready to take Horſe, the grand <hi>Provo Caſteneda,</hi> comes with Forty at his heels, ſhewing me no Order, conveyes my Son and I to the Priſon called <hi>Urinate,</hi> and Orders that none ſhould come to ſpeak unto us, which ſo continued for ſix Months, we ſtarving with hunger and cold, after which I found means to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs unty my Sacred King, who was ſo indulgently juſt, that he did authorize the Judge Millitary of <hi>Flanders</hi> to examine the proceedings,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:99819:16"/> as alſo to determine who ſo did as heretofore is declared, which compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes his Catholick Majeſties Orders, to pay the charges of my impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment who had nothing to do with it, and to put me at liberty, that was made Priſoner <hi>ſine culpa:</hi> To give an allay unto my unjuſt ſufferances, this Order did not a little ſolace me.</p>
               <p n="13">XIII. One thing Noble Reader, I being admitted Pen and Ink, be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to obſerve; I did ever renounce my Kings Grace or Favour, ſhould I be made guilty of Diſloyalty; I would neither beg, deſire, or take my Kings Pardon, I never having ſinned againſt him, his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, or Service; nor would I my Gods pardon, had I no more ſinned againſt him, than I have againſt my King. I then in my time of Impriſonment, did repreſent unto my King that a time would come that the Lord <hi>Digby,</hi> and Sir <hi>Edward Hyde</hi> would be Caſhier'd, and Baniſhed from his Court; and that I who was then Tyrannically made Priſoner by their falſe Informations and Suggeſtions, ſhould be at liberty to ſtand at His Majeſties Elboe, to ſee them both in diſgrace, and ſo I have, and ſeen them; and ſeeing I could not then there poſſeſs the true liberty due to a Subject, I would I may here, which hitherto I have not. I may implore, nay preſs for it, <hi>Conſcientia mille Teſtes;</hi> I fear no man upon Earth, my Duty to my King not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed, nor no Laws either: My King I am ſure cannot in himſelf err. So good I am ſure he is, I cannot nor will I ſay that Miniſters of State, who govern the conſciences of Kings, and who are to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer may not err: This I intend unto the Miniſters of Forraign Kings.</p>
               <p n="14">XIV. You muſt know Noble Reader, that the City of <hi>Bruxels</hi> have it by their Charter, that no ſtranger made Priſoner there, is to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained above Twenty four hours without he be Examined, his Charge given in againſt him, and the Cauſe of his Impriſonment Examined and that beſides, if any make a Priſoner upon Informations, that they ſhould ſecure to make a party againſt the Priſoner; who by their Law in <hi>Bruxels</hi> are to allow the Priſoner a daily ſubſiſtence, according to the Quality of the Priſoner, elſe the Priſoner not to be detained. Upon which it was ordered that I, and my Son, and ſervant, by His Moſt Excellent Majeſties then Councel, that Twenty pence a day ſhould be given us. The World may judge whether that was a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion fit, and I having lain Thirty three months Priſoner. Sir <hi>Steven Fox</hi> being ordered to pay that conſiderable allowance; yet for the time of Thirty three months I never received but Ten pound or about the Value. I do not ſay this to upbraid Sir <hi>Steven,</hi> for I believe him an honeſt Gentleman; but that mony was then not over plenty in his Treaſury. I being forced to addreſs unto the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> he ſet me at liberty, and payed my Coſts as here aforeſaid, elſe I had there periſhed.</p>
               <p n="15">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:99819:17"/>XV. I appeal unto my Moſt Gracious King for Juſtice, who never did deny it unto any of his Subjects, and I ſhall ever, as now I do ſubmit unto his will and pleaſure. I having ever ſerved under his Royal Banner, and never had a hand in the War of <hi>Ireland;</hi> I had many of my Kings Letters and Orders, to have my Eſtate not to be made liable unto new Quit Rents, and years Value, which never had or took the leaſt effects: I have payed ever ſince His Majeſties happy Reſtauration for yearly Quit Rents, at Two pence Farthing an Acre out of my Eſtate, an Hundred and Three pound odd mony yearly, as is certified under the Auditor Generals hand out of <hi>Ireland;</hi> which amounts not far in the time from being 1900 l. and the years full Value for one year of my Eſtate, beſides Morgages upon my Eſtate of above a Thouſand pound; which I engaged for to bring Horſe and Foot for His Majeſties Service out of <hi>Ireland.</hi> I muſt attribute it to my fate, or the want of meeting with Juſtice, whereas I am put in Ballance with ſuch as were in Actual Arms, and Service againſt their Majeſty. Nay, a great many of ſuch have had their Eſtates ſtruck out of charge, and their Quit rents taken off, yet mine ſtill ſtand charged. His Majeſties Orders and Letters, as to my particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar meeting with no obedience: If looſers may ſpeak, ſure none can blame me for this my Declaration, having never had the leaſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation, gift or grant, nor other uſage than what herein is ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; only One hundered pound from the Privy Purſe. To this my Vindication or Declaration I ſet my hand, and am ready to juſtifie it; by either Common, Civil, or Military Law, or place of Juſtice againſt any man, that dare to my face contradict what I here have ſaid; let him be Subject, <hi>French, Dutch,</hi> or any Forreigner. If any be here, he may find the lie given him, and he will ſwallow it, or give his appearance to charge me.</p>
               <p n="16">XVI. Sir <hi>Robert Walſh</hi> hath been detained Three years Priſoner to the <hi>French</hi> King in the <hi>Baſtil,</hi> and never any thing laid to his Charge; but for being of the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi>'s party. Then he came for <hi>England,</hi> and was made Priſoner in the Tower by the Uſurper, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any thing laid to his Charge. Then was made Priſoner in <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xels</hi> by his Kings Miniſters, and never any thing laid to his Charge before Juſtice. Theſe Impriſonments were all, you I hope will ſay hard; here lately made Priſoner to the Black Rod, and nothing laid to his Charge in 79. Is this the liberty of the Subject?</p>
               <p n="17">XVII. One thing more I may with Juſtice add, I being in <hi>Paris</hi> about the year 72. or 73. or thereabouts I had by the means of <hi>Monſieur de Mumbas</hi> my ancient Acquaintance, who was Brother in Law unto <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niere de Grote, alias Grotius</hi> then Embaſſador for the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> an entrance unto this Embaſſador, ſo as that I did diſcover that the <hi>French</hi> King, and the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> were then upon the point, and but very little difference between them of coming unto an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:99819:17"/> or Joyning, His Grace the Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> then having His Majeſty's Ear, I immediatly writ to him, that it would be of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great conſequence to prevent the ſaid junction, by an agreement with the States; which as I take did very ſoon iſſue, <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> having until of late continued in a War, my Letter unto his Grace I addreſt to Sir <hi>John Hanmer,</hi> who did tell me ſince my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into <hi>England,</hi> that ſuch a Letter he did receive from me, and that he believe it did ſtill lye by him, I writ at the ſame time to Mr. <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> to the ſame purpoſe, who I am ſure did ſhow or produce it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to His Majeſty, unto whom I ſent <hi>Miniere Grotius</hi> his Letter to me in Mr. <hi>Montegue</hi> his Packet, as may be judged by the effects of the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation then we made with the States; and Mr. <hi>Edward Progers</hi> his Letter was to have me come in Perſon into <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="19">XIX. The Year of His Majeſties happy reſtauration, the <hi>Marquis de Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance</hi> was commiſſioned by the <hi>French</hi> King to come unto His Moſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Majeſty to <hi>London,</hi> upon ſome pretext from the <hi>French</hi> King, <hi>Dunkerk</hi> then in the Lord <hi>Lockerts</hi> time of Government there, and newly rendered unto His Moſt Excellent Majeſty: the <hi>Marquis de Gudance,</hi> made it his work to gain ſome Officers of the Gariſon of <hi>Dunkerk,</hi> to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe the Gariſon for the <hi>French</hi> King, and had contracted a Treaty with them for that purpoſe, Sir <hi>Robert Walſh</hi> then living at <hi>Berge</hi> St. <hi>Venox</hi> a League from <hi>Dunkerk,</hi> this <hi>Marquis</hi> came to <hi>Berge</hi> often, he and Sir <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> came acquainted, ſo as the <hi>Marquis</hi> did communicate his deſign up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Dunkerk</hi> to Sir <hi>Robert,</hi> ſounding him that knew the humor of the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh,</hi> how he might ſo confide in the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and to prevent and be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cautioned that he may not be trapanned, he offering Sir <hi>Robert</hi> an aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Five Thouſand Piſtols, If he would contribute by his advice and conduct. Which Sir <hi>Robert</hi> did conſent to yield unto, reſerving to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to do his duty to his King; immediatly hereupon, he humbly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed a Letter to His Majeſty, whereupon His Sacred Majeſty imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly writ to Sir <hi>Robert</hi> in his own hand, immediatly to repair un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him with all ſpeed and privacy. Unto which Sir <hi>Robert</hi> quit his Houſe, dwelling and intereſt in <hi>Berge</hi> St. <hi>Venox,</hi> and immediatly came to His Majeſty. The now Earl of <hi>Arlington</hi> being then Secretary of State, His Majeſty did Order Sir <hi>Robert</hi> to make his addreſs unto him, and to communicate all particulars unto him, which Sir <hi>Robert</hi> ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, my Lord gave thereunto a hearing anſwerable, and did receive Sir <hi>Robert</hi> with expreſſions very kind, of the ſenſe he had of Sir <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berts</hi> ſervice in that particular, and that he would in Order there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto give His Majeſty an account; unfortunately ſoon after Sir <hi>Robert</hi> was arreſted for a Hundred Pound, and committed Priſoner to the Fleet, under Chancellor <hi>Hide</hi> his Verge, who made ſuch uſe of his power; carrying an animoſity againſt Sir <hi>Robert,</hi> that notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sir <hi>Robert</hi> had put in good ſecurity, he could not obtain a day writ, Sir <hi>Jeremy Witchcot</hi> being ſo much the Chancellors Creature, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the Lord <hi>Arlington</hi> who was not ſo, writ to the Warden of the Fleet Sir <hi>Jeremy Witchcot,</hi> that it was His Majeſties pleaſure, Sir <hi>Robert</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:99819:18"/> ſhould have a day writ, which Letter Sir <hi>Robert</hi> this day hath, and upon which his day writ was had; and His Majeſty a little time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter did order Sir <hi>Robert</hi> a Hundred Pound, which was brought him to the <hi>Fleet,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Arlington</hi> did alſo make Sir <hi>Robert</hi> a preſent of Twenty Ginneys: unto my Lord <hi>Arlington,</hi> the Lord Chancellor (a thing not unknown) was then no great friend; yet the Lord <hi>Arling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> Loyalty, Fidelity, and duty to his King, hath ſo preſerved him as to be now what he hath deſerved, and is, and ſo may all taſte as they deſerve, if not in this world, in the next they muſt and will, but as unto, <hi>Dunkerk</hi> ſuch order was then given, as that the <hi>French</hi> Kings deſign took not, until it was ſold him, which I wiſh had never been: Sir <hi>Robert</hi> could ſay more but hates to trample upon the dead. This was after <hi>Sir Roberts</hi> being kept Priſoner in <hi>Bruxels,</hi> by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigation of Chancellor <hi>Hyde,</hi> and the inſtrument he made uſe of to have <hi>Sir Robert</hi> then made Priſoner, was one that ingratiated himſelf with <hi>Don John D' Auſtrea,</hi> who was then Governor of <hi>Planders,</hi> which was thus, he was an <hi>Engliſh</hi> man and a degree above a Knight, he being ſome years ſervant unto an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Dame, who had had Three or Four Children, he had her received by <hi>Don John</hi> for a Maid, and ſo paſt her for unto him, and ſome Five or <hi>Six</hi> Hundred Piſtols was gained that way, this was not ill mis-trip, as ſome that read this well may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the paſſage herein, ſuch qualified perſons, not conſtant in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Proteſtant or Papiſt, were the inſtruments of <hi>Sir Robert Walſh</hi> his Murderous Impriſonment, for Three and Thirty Months in <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xels,</hi> but they never would come as witneſſes in this age do, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to maintain their accuſations either by right or wrong, thoſe who Treacherouſly under hand to gain them a little favor, were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſors of <hi>Sir Robert Walſh,</hi> he could name Six of them ſince gone un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a worſe World then this, and few or none now living.</p>
               <p n="20">XX. Now Noble Reader, this <hi>Everard</hi> daſhing at me, that I ſhould be a ſubduer of Diſcoveries, Animoſities, Plots, or Deſigns, intended towards the ſubverſion of His Majeſties Laws and Government, to prove how far from truth that is, I appeal to what my King know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, as coming from me in 1675. 76. 77. 78. And what I did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate unto the now Honorable Lord Chancellor, the Lord <hi>Arling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> and other Miniſters in or about the ſaid years, whoſe names I now mention not, as unwilling to add calamity unto calamity. I doubt ſome whom I would have named in 1675. were I thereunto ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon'd, are no ſmall Incendiaries or Promotors in Diſturbances. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which had I been heard in time, prevention might have been gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the World cannot but Judge, and ſo ſhall, that my intereſt is ſoly in my Sovereigns, and that of his good Subjects, I having ſtaid here theſe Four years, in expectance that my Repreſentments ſhould be verified and ſo allowed as now they are; and to my great coſt I have my Labor for my pains, <hi>ſed Tempus edax rerum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="21">
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:99819:18"/>XXI. Now Noble Reader, pardon if I give you the trouble of reading, how the <hi>Sieur Grimings</hi> was put to death, who was the Receiver Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of <hi>Planders,</hi> a Perſon then moſt High and Eminent, would make Princes attend their having Audience, whiles he ſtayed to ſee his Daughters dance the <hi>Tricote;</hi> his Pallace in <hi>Bruxels,</hi> not much infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior to <hi>Dunkerk</hi> or <hi>Clarendon</hi> houſe: the reaſon why I trouble you your Reading his end, is that I was nominated in bringing him to it, he then being a Priſoner, in the ſame which I was in at <hi>Bruxels,</hi> in the year 1658. that I was the Perſon, who next his demeanor of not being capable to account, for the vaſt ſumms he had received, of his Catholick Majeſties Subjects, that I was the perſon who hindered his eſcape, a thing I then did own and now do, which none living can or will blame me for, when they here the truth, as now here they may of the paſſages thereof, yet did Sir <hi>Edward Hide</hi> and his then Creatures, falſely aſperſe me, in giving out that I betrayed this <hi>Grim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> the paſſages were as thus, which is the Real truth of it: this <hi>Grimings</hi> being a cloſe Priſoner in a ground Chamber, ſeeing me walk in the Yard, had the opportunity of asking me why I was there a Priſoner. I replied I did not know, and withal, that I renounced the Grace or Favor of all Kings or Law, for any thing that could be laid to my charge, upon which he ſaid that the Kings grace was not to be denied, and I replied not for them who had uſe thereof; of which number I did conclude he was one, and ſo we parted; his Lady was then confined to his Pallace in <hi>Bruxels,</hi> and a Hundred Soldiers there every Night in Guard, ſhe hearing that I was a perſon of Honor and a Priſoner, which lay in the Chamber above her Husband, ſhe diſgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes herſelf and comes to my Chamber, throws herſelf at my feet, which very much did ſurprize me, I made her riſe, which ſhe was unwilling unto, ſhe declaring that I was the only perſon that could relieve and ſerve her, I ſaid that ſure ſhe was miſtaken, and that ſhe took me for ſome other more conſiderable Perſon, that might be a Priſoner, ſhe cryed no, that it was I, and none other elſe that could ſerve her, and declares unto me how, which was as thus, my Husband lyeth here under your Chamber, and I can no way contrive a Communication with him, but by your means, help and aſſiſtance. If that you may pleaſe ſo far to be charitably oblieging towards me, as to contrive his having a Billet from me, for all his Wealth lyeth placed in convents and particular places, that without my having an account from him, how and where, I and my Children are ruined for ever. Unto which I replied, that I lay Priſoner I knew not for what, and for to render my ſelf to be guilty of Intermedling in a concern of that Nature, could ſhew no Judgment or wiſdom in me, but ſhe ſo did importune me that ſhe prevailed, and I did contrive to convey her Billets to her Husband, and his to her, by which means ſhe found where and how all his Wealth lay, upon which ſhe got his Wealth, which were Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of Livers, and ſo conveyed herſelf into <hi>Holland,</hi> out of the King of <hi>Spains</hi> Dominions, without making me the leaſt return, but by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of her Letters which are yet extant, <hi>Grimings</hi> being put upon the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:99819:19"/> Rack, confeſſed contrary to his Vows and promiſes, that it was by my means that he correſponded with his Wife, upon which his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Majeſty ſent Commiſſioners to examine me, who indeed were very civil; I did not deny my guilt, ſaying why did his Catholick Majeſty detain me Priſoner, and upon what grounds: The Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners ſaid I had given great Treaſures out of His Majeſties Cophers, ſoon after <hi>Grimings</hi> his Wife run away, I writ to <hi>Grimings,</hi> that I had ſerved him in the truſt his Wife impoſed in me, and deſired him that he would give his Billet to his ſon; for me to receive a Hundred Piſtols, I being in diſtreſs, which he would not do, then I writ to him, that he ſhould never expect any favor at my hand, but to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry as he found by the loſs of his Head. For he being juſt ready to have made his eſcape, I did diſcover it to <hi>Don John d' Auſtrea,</hi> and to the <hi>Marquis de Caraſſenas,</hi> being in no truſt for <hi>Grimings,</hi> for he intended to have got into the <hi>French</hi> quarters, and being a perſon that was in ſo conſiderable an Imployment and poſture as he was, he would have diſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved his Catholick Majeſty to a greater value, then the vaſt ſumms of his Majeſties that he could not account for, which I prevented and made His Catholick Majeſty amends for what I formerly did for <hi>Grimings,</hi> who as unto his being ungrateful, did meet the due return, by my means in which he did not intruſt me. I long ſince made a Declaration of this matter, the Year of His Majeſties happy reſtauration, who was gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly pleaſed to write unto me to come into <hi>England,</hi> all in his own hand, which I did obey: I then declared that the Chancellor of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> for his ill managing the Kings Conſcience, being chief Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, was degraded. Soe was <hi>Monſieur Fouquet</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> that was Treaſurer: Then how <hi>Grimings</hi> in <hi>Flanders</hi> loſt his head, and I did fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee that the next bordering Miniſter ſhould take example in being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cautioned, I addreſſing the ſame to the Lord <hi>Clarendon,</hi> who had me Priſoner under his Laſh in the <hi>Fleet,</hi> I then ſhewed my Declaration unto that Honorable Perſon the Lord of <hi>Angliſey,</hi> Lord Privy Seal not to conceal the ſight thereof from my Lord <hi>Clarendon,</hi> which my Lord of <hi>Angliſey</hi> did not, ſo as in a little time after my Lord <hi>Clarendon,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not ſo vehement in the Execution of his Power. <hi>Falix quem faciunt aliena pericula cautum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="22">XXII. This is to declare the Ingratitude of the ſaid <hi>Grimings,</hi> and what his not Provoyance did bring him unto; he having been put on the Torture did confeſs, that it was by my means, that his Wife did beget a Correſpondence with him, to attain unto his wealth as ſhe hath; I being Examined therein by His Catholick Majeſties Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſaries, who ſhewed me; how <hi>Grimings</hi> did own it was I who gave the Expedient; and they carrying themſelves very civilly towards me, I did own, that I was, if it was a Guilt. The helper of giving the Acceſs of her Billets to her Husband, and his unto her; ſaying; why did His Catholick Majeſty keep me a Priſoner without producing my Charge; what had he to ſay againſt me, I renounced either Grace or Favour from him, I demanded Juſtice; withal declaring that the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:99819:19"/> Tyranny of my ſo being kept Priſoner, might have given me ſcope, to have ſerved all Priſoners, as ſuppoſing that they might be as guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs as I was. This <hi>Grimings</hi> after his being put to the Torture, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns to endeavour making his eſcape, and begets an underſtanding with one that was then there Priſoner, to help him unto Files, to file the Iron Barrs of his Grate, which he did, I having diſſerved His Catholick Majeſty and willing to repair the ſame, I lodging above <hi>Grimings,</hi> in the Night I could hear him file the Iron Barrs, and taking notice thereof, I did walking in the Yard diſcover the Bar of Iron he worked upon, and was very near effecting his deſign, I lying under His Catholick? Majeſties diſpleaſure, I did calculate, that if I made a Diſcovery of his intent to have eſcaped, it might have allayed the former diſobligement I had layed on His Catholick Majeſty, and I being not ſatisfied with the ingratitude of <hi>Grimings</hi> and his Wife; ſo as I writ unto <hi>Don John d' Auſtrea,</hi> how <hi>Grimings</hi> was to have made his eſcape. Whereupon he ſent to find the Utiles, and to ſearch every corner of his Chamber, but found no viſibility of what I had repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, his having ſent Commiſſaries and a Glaſier to ſound the Bars, but they could diſcover no appearance; ſo <hi>Don John</hi> ſent to me, that I repreſented what was not true. I returned to <hi>Don John,</hi> that thoſe he ſent were Fools; and gave them direction how to diſcover the truth of what I repreſented, and ſo they did. You muſt know, that when they came with a Key to ſound the Iron Bars, the Bars did ſound all ſound, which in a cut Bar is not ordinary. But <hi>Grimings,</hi> as ſoon as he filed, did fill the Oraphis with wax and Tobacco-powder, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til I gave the Key of this diſcovery, they could not find it out; but having found it he was ſoon Executed, and all the favour he could obtain, who was once the Great <hi>Grimings,</hi> was to have his head chopt off in the ſaid Priſon, and was not carried to the Common Place of Execution.</p>
               <p n="23">XXIII. I muſt a little here diſplay in part, what return or reward I met with, for my coming out of <hi>France,</hi> with my Repreſentments of the diſturbances, which were intended towards the deturnment of His Sacred Majeſties Laws and Government. I having been for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Years out of <hi>England,</hi> upon my arrival here in <hi>London,</hi> I was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced to the Widow of a <hi>Hamborow</hi> Merchant, by Name <hi>E. I.</hi> now <hi>O. B.</hi> ſhe was repreſented for a very Rich Widow; we falling into acquaintance, ſhe very much did importune me to lodge at her Houſe, which I did for a week, not without repreſenting unto her, that it would bring her name under a ſenſure, ſeeing that there was no concern as unto any thing of Marriage in the point, for inſtead of every Thouſand Pounds, ſaid ſhe had, that proved but Four or Five great Sons, and a Daughter, which I finding, as alſo diſcovering her Goſſoping and Frolicking qualities, I withdrew in my viſits and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quency with her, whereupon ſhe grew moſt outragiouſly inveterate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, and whereas her Letr ers of which I have a Buſhel, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that my ſheets ſhould be well aired, and I ſhould be kept warm,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:99819:20"/> and that all her all was mine, and in her Letters declaring, that ſhe pretended not to have the honor of marrying a perſon of my quality, only coveting my Company. The cruel uſage of hers as followeth; may admit my thus expatiating, though a thing contrary, to my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture towards that venerable Sex: It's true, that in the time of our converſe, I did tell her that there would be great diſturbances and troubles ingendred in <hi>England,</hi> I ſoon after refraining giving her my viſits, ſhe grew paſſionately deſperate, run out one night out of her Houſe into the ſtreet, ſtopt my Coach, ſhe half naked; and ſwore if I came not in and ſtay all night, that ſhe would kill herſelf. I not ſtaying as being unwilling thereunto, ſhe a little after went in her paſſion to my Lord Chief Juſtice, and made a moſt pernitious and falſe <hi>affidavit,</hi> that I robbed her of a Hundred Pounds worth of Plate, and that I had pawnd it, unto Mr. <hi>John wallis</hi> a Gold-ſmith in <hi>Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard</hi> ſtreet, at the ſign of the <hi>Angel,</hi> who can witneſs that I never did pawn any Plate unto him, a Perſon in whoſe hands, I intruſted ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of mine to be kept, above Two Hundred Pounds, and that if any was pawnd that ſhe pawnd it herſelf, and afterwards ſhe came to Mr. <hi>Wallis,</hi> and fain would have retrieved her Plate, ſaying that ſhe only ſent it him to be Varniſhed, this Mr. <hi>wallis</hi> a man of fame and credit will aver; but as unto her falſe <hi>Affidavid,</hi> ſhe procured the Lord Chief Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice his Warrant, and in comes the Tipſtaff one <hi>Otway,</hi> with Twenty or Thirty at his heels, and I ſcarce out of my bed, they hurried me half naked through the ſtreet, and carried me to <hi>New priſon,</hi> where I lay Two or Three hours, ſent for Bail, who entred into rcogniſance of Two Thouſand Pounds, for my appearance as <hi>Hick's-Hall,</hi> which I did, and the Gentlemen ſitting there cancelled my recogniſance, and took Two ordinary men bound in Twenty Pounds a peace, and I in Forty to appear at <hi>Guild-hall</hi> the following Seſſions, to anſwer to the Indictment againſt me for the King, put in by this Widow <hi>E. J.</hi> now <hi>O. B.</hi> unto which I did appear at <hi>Guild-Hall,</hi> before the Lord Chief Juſtice and that Honorable Bench, a Jury being Impanneld, ſhe appearing there and telling her Story, the Lord Chief Juſtice and the Bench, found it ſo nonſenſical as my Lord told the Jury, that there was no Subject for them to be troubled with, ſo diſmiſſed them and me from the indictment, though ſhe pretended to have compriſed me in the Number of ſuch as were concerned in the Plot. This. Widow <hi>E. I.</hi> now <hi>O. B.</hi> did abſolutely give unto Sir <hi>Robert walſh</hi> a Dubble guilt Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard, which is under her own hand, and arreſted by <hi>John Chappel Clearke</hi> unto Sir <hi>James Butler, Sarah Sing</hi> and <hi>Frances Duval,</hi> the ſaid Tankard Sir <hi>Robert</hi> made a preſent of, unto a Perſon of quality, yet the ſaid Widow moſt impudently did make her addreſs unto the ſaid Perſon of quality, and did perſwade him that Sir <hi>Robert</hi> rob'd her of her Tankard, and the ſaid Perſon of quality could not be rid of her importunity until he gave her the Tankard, without having asked Sir <hi>Robert</hi> of the matter; they being at a far diſtance one from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I had at <hi>Guild-Hall</hi> under her own hand Forty of her Letter, to produce what ſhe was, which are ſtill extant. In one ſhe writes, that
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:99819:20"/> ſhe was ſo much in the favor of Sir <hi>J. E.</hi> as that ſhe was ſure if his Wife, who was ſickly ſhould dye, that he would marry her, and that if ſo, I ſhould be her Gallant, and I ſhould not want for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, this Letter and all hers are this day extant.</p>
               <p n="24">XXIV. In the Year 1655. or 1656, I being here intruſted as is ſet forth in my manifeſt, to ſteal away then from the Uſurpers claws, I was neceſſitated, to take up Forty Pounds worth in ſilk Stockings, to carry me into <hi>Flanders,</hi> I being here in 1677. I was arreſted upon my Bond of Forty Pounds, and forced to pay Sixty five Pounds, as Mr. <hi>John Wallis</hi> Gold-ſmith, and <hi>Sargent Dike</hi> in whoſe Priſon <hi>I</hi> was can witneſs, yet <hi>I</hi> importuned not His Majeſty to my relief as in that. <hi>I</hi> lying Priſoner upon the ſtocking action, comes an action of Four Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Pound againſt me, upon Bond in the Year 1641. where <hi>I</hi> then became bound for the Lord <hi>Henry wilmot,</hi> late Earl of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> which was to carry him then after His Majeſty of Bleſſed Memory to <hi>York:</hi> This action being laid upon me, <hi>I</hi> did petition and implore, His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty to look upon the hardneſs of my paying that debt, which the Duke of <hi>Ormond</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Bathe,</hi> did repreſent unto His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, who was compaſſionate, but <hi>I</hi> was forced to ſatisfie the debt, which <hi>I</hi> could not then have done, but that a great Lord and a great Subject, did ſo take me into his conſideration, as that he did relieve me, he is not now in this Kingdom, but is in one of His Majeſties, <hi>I</hi> dare not mention his Name, knowing he is not Covetous, that his charitable goodneſs, in ſuch kind ſhould eſclat. Theſe are the rewards <hi>I</hi> meet with, in return of my coming of purpoſe out of <hi>France</hi> in the Year 1675. To have diſcovered the inſurrections and diſturbances, which were intended againſt His Majeſties Kingdoms and good Subjects, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no other for my labor, charges, and loſs of time here theſe Four Years paſt, then have been theſe misfortunes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The Concluſion of my Manifeſt.</head>
               <p>I Beg the favor from you Noble Readers, not to cenſure as that <hi>I</hi> vaunt of my ſervices, having done but my duty, or that <hi>I</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of the Murderous impriſonment, <hi>I</hi> have for Three and Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Months, with <hi>I</hi> may ſay injuſtice groaned under, which <hi>I</hi> impute unto the moſt ungrounded ill conduct of ſome then Miniſters of State, who gave ear unto ſome falſe Raſcally and moſt Villanous intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers: Some of which may live this day, and read herein the Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter <hi>I</hi> give them, whoſe courage affords them not to take notice, the beſt of men doth know who they where or be, <hi>I</hi> do not, <hi>I</hi> would <hi>I</hi> did; they ſoon ſhould here from me, who am His Majeſties Loyal Subject, and unto you my friends an humble Servant.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>July 3. 1679.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Robert Walſh</hi> Knight and Ba<hi rend="sup">tt</hi>.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
